<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The goodli history of the moste noble and beautyfull Ladye Lucres of Scene in Tuskane, and of her louer Eurialus verye pleasaunt and delectablevnto ye reder</title>
            <title>De duobus amantibus Eurialo et Lucrecia. English</title>
            <author>Pius, II, Pope, 1404-1464.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1553</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113407</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848641</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848641</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09706)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1690:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The goodli history of the moste noble and beautyfull Ladye Lucres of Scene in Tuskane, and of her louer Eurialus verye pleasaunt and delectablevnto ye reder</title>
                  <title>De duobus amantibus Eurialo et Lucrecia. English</title>
                  <author>Pius, II, Pope, 1404-1464.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Day,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1553?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Pope Pius II.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks last leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13750:1"/>
            <p>¶ The goodli hiſtory of the moſte noble and beautyfull Ladye Lucres of Scene in Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kane, and of her louer Eurialus verye pleaſaunt and delectable vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reder</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13750:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13750:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Emperour Sigiſmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d enteryng into the town of Scene in Tuſkane, what honours he receiued: is all redy euery wher publiſhed His palayce was prepared at ſaint Marthies chapel, in the ſtrete that ledeth vn to the poſterne, called To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phore. After the ceremonis finiſhed, when Sigiſmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was come thider, foure ladies in noblenes, facion, age and apparell ſemblable, did mete hym not lyke mortal women: but as goddes, to euery mans iudgmente and if they had ben but thre they had ben to be rekened the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Paris ſaw in his dreme. Sigiſmond (thoughe he wer aged) was prone vnto luſt, and delited much in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireing with ladies, and reioiſed in bla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſments of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men nor nothing was to him more pleſaunt, then to be hold goodly women. Then in aduiſynge them (vnlike to the reſt) he was receiued from his horſe among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and turning to his familiers ſaid, ſaw ye euer any like to theſe women? I am in doubt whether theſe faces be mankynde, or aungels, but ſurely they are heauenly. They caſting their eine to the ground in bluſhyng be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam fayrer, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ruddy fluſhing in their chekes gaue ſuch a colour to their countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as hath the yud iue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſtoined with the ſcarlet, or the whit lilies among the purple roſes: But among al: Lucres the yonge Ladye, not yet of twenty yeres, ſhone in great bryghtnes yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g maryed in the famyly of the Camilles, vnto a very rich man, named Menelaus, vnworthy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch.
<pb facs="tcp:13750:3"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:13750:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13750:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>beautye ſhulde ſerue at home: but well worthye of hys wyfe to be deceyued. The ſtature of the Lady Lucres was more hygher than the other. Her he are plenteous and lyke vnto the goulde wyre, whyche hanged not downe behynde her, after the manner and cuſtome of maydens: but in goulde and ſtone ſhe had encloſed it, her forhed hyghe of ſemelye ſpace, wythoute wrynkell, her browes bente, facyoned wythfe we he ares, by due ſpace deuyded, her eyne ſhynyng wyth ſuch bryghtnes that lyke as the ſonne, they ouercame the behoulders lokyng: wyth thoſe ſhe myght whome ſhe woulde, flee (and ſlayne) when ſhe wold reuyue. Strayt as thriede was her nooſe, and by euen deuiſion parted, her fayre chekes, nothing was more amiable, then theſe chekes nor nothyng more delectable to behold, wherin (whan ſhe did laughe) appeared two proper pyties, why<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> no man dyd ſe, that wiſhed not to haue kyſſed. Her mouth ſmall and comely, her lyppes of corall colour, handſom to hyte on her ſmall tethe, wel ſet in order, ſemed Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal through which the quiuering tonge dyd ſend furth (not wordes) but mooſt pleaſant armony. What ſhall I ſhe we the beautye of her chynne, or the whyteneſſe of her necke? Nothynge was in that bodye not too bee prayſed as the outwarde aparaunces ſhewed token of that that was inwarde, no man beheld her that dyd not enuy her huſbande, ſhe was in ſpeche as the fame is, that the mother of Graccus was, or the daughter of Hortentius. Nothynge was more ſweter, nor ſoberer than her talcke. She pretended not (as dothe many) honeſtye by heuy countenance: but with mery vyſage, ſhewed her ſobernes, not fearefull, nor ouer he ardye: but vnder d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſhe cared in a womans hart
<pb facs="tcp:13750:4"/>Her apparell was dyuers, ſhe wanted nether broches, borders, gyrdels, nor rynges. The abilimentes of her head, was ſumptuouſe, many pearles, many dyaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, were on her fyngers and in her borders. I thyncke the day that the Greeke Menelaus feeſted Paris. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len was no fayrer: Nor Adromaches no more gorgeus when ſhee was marryed vnto Hector. And amonge thoſe, was Katheryne of Peruſia, that ſhortelye aftere dyed, in whoſe funerals the Emperour was prefounte (and thoughe he were but a chylde) made her Sonne knyght, at her ſepulchre, and of her the beautye was al ſo meruelouſe: but nothyng ſo greate, as of Lucres.</p>
            <p>Her dyd the Emperoure Sigiſmonde, and all othere, prayſe and beholde, but one amonge theym, more than ynoughe was ſette vppon here. ¶ Eurialus of the contre of Francony, whome neyther ſhap nor rycheſſe cauſed to be vnmere to loue, hee was of the age of two and thyrty yeres, not very hygh of ſtature, but of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and pleaſant facion, wyth noble eyne, his chekes ruddy and fayre, as the white lilies amonge the purple roſes, his other members (as who ſayeth) with a ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes of ſhape correſpondent to his ſtature. The other courtiers by long w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> poore. Hee beſydes his owne ſubſtaunce, by famylyarytie wyth the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure, receyued daylye rewardes. Hee was more and more gorgeouſe in ſyghte of menne, and lede a greate trayne of ſeruauntes after hym, and he hadde ſuche a horſe (as the tale reporteth) as Mennon hadde, whan he came to Troye. Nothyng he wanted to prouoke the ſame hete of the mynde, called loue, but onlye ydlenes Yet, youth luſt, and the glad goodes of fortune, wyth whyche thynges hee was well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ouercame
<pb facs="tcp:13750:5"/>hym out of hys owne power. Eurialus, as ſone as he had ſene Lucres, he brent in the loue of the Lady, and fyxyng hys eyen in her face, neuer thought he to haue ſene ynough, yet loued he not in vayne, it is a wounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe thynge, there were manye goodly yong men but Lucres had only choſen this, there were manye good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly women: but Eurialus had choſen her onlye. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles, not at that time knewe Lucres the fame of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialus towarde her, nor he hers, but eche one of theym thought to haue loued in vayne.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ceremonyes vnto the Emperoure fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, ſhee retourned whome, hoole vowed vnto Eurialus, and Eurialus clene geuen vnto Lucres, remayneth. Who nowe ſhulde maruell of the rale of Piramys and Thyſbe? betwyxte whome, bothe acquayntaunce and neyghbourhode myghte be entre of theyr loue, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tyme grewe theyre loue. Theeſe louers Eurialus and Lucres, neuer ſawe nor hearde afore eyther of othere, he a Franconyen, and ſhe a Tuſkan, nor in theeſe bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenes they occupyed not theyr tongues: but it was all done with eye ne, ſythens that the one ſo pleaſed thee other. Lucres then wounded wyth greuous care, and taken wyth thee blynde fyre, forgettynge all readye that ſhee is maryed, hateth her huſbande, and wyth woundes nouryſhynge the wounde, holdeth fyxed in her breſt the countenaunce and face of Eurialus, nor geueth no maner reaſt vnto her lymmes, and with her ſelfe ſayth, I wote not what letteth me that I can no more companye wyth my huſbande, nothyng delyteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hynge pleaſeth me hys kyſſes
<pb facs="tcp:13750:5"/>hys wordes anoye me ſo ſtandeth alwayes afore myne eyen the ymage of the ſtraunger that to day was nexte vnto the Emperour. Caſte halas, oh vnhappye, oute of my chaſte breaſt that conceyued ſtames yf thou maye, yf I myghte, halas, I ſhoulde not be as I am, euell at eaſe. A new kynd of ſtrength agaynſt my wyl draweth me, my deſyre and my reaſon meueth me dyuerſlye, I knowe the beſt, and the worſte I folowe. Oh Noble ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezen, what haſt thou to do wyth an vnknowne man? why brenneſt thou in a ſtraungers loue? whye ſeekeſt thou thy luſt in a ſtraung countrye? yf thy huſband lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the thyne owne countrye maye geue the that thou loueſt. Oh, but what a maner of face hathe he? what woman woulde not be meaued wyth hys beauty, youth noblenes, and vertue? ſurely I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and wythoute hys help I deſpayre, God graunt vs better. Shal I betray halas, the chaſte ſpouſels. and betake me too a ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, I wotte not whence? which when he hath abuſed me, ſhall departe, and ſhall be an others, and ſo leaue me be hynde, but by his countenaunce, it is not lyke to be ſo, and the noblenes of hys mynde ſeameth not to be ſuch, nor ſo pretendeth not the grace of hys beuty that I ſhuld fere diſceyt or his forgetting of loue. And he ſhal promiſe aforehande aſſured, whye do I dreade? I ſhall apply it without ferther abrode, parde, I am ſo fayre that hee wyll no leſſe deſyre me, than I hym, hee ſhall be myne for euer, yf ones I maye receyue hym to my kyſſes. How many do woo me where ſo euer I go? how many ryuals do watche afore my dore? I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to loue, eyther he ſhall tary here, or at hys depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng cary me wyth hym. Shall I than forſake my mo thee, my huſbande, and my countr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13750:6"/>warde and alwayes agaynſte myne appetites my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande I had rather wante, than haue, my countrey is ther as I delyte to dwell, but ſhal I ſo leaſe my fame? whye not? what haue I to doo wyth mennes woordes whyche I ſhal not here? Nothynge ſhall he dare, that feareth the threatnyng of fame, many other haue don the ſame. Helena woulde bee rauyſhed. Paris caryed hee not away againſt her wyl. What ſhal I tel of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na or Medea? no man blameth the fauter that fauteth with many. Thus ſaid Lucres nor within his breaſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nouryſhed Eurialus no leſſe flames.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the mid way, betwixt the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours court, and Eurialus loging was Lucreſes houſe, &amp; Eurialus myght not go vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pallace, but ſhowing her ſelf out of the highe windowes, was in his ein but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Lucres bluſſhed, whan ſhe ſaw Eurialus, whych thyng gaue vnto the Emperour knowlege of the loue. For as by cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtome he vſed to ride here &amp; ther, paſſyng often y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> way, he ſawe the woman chaunge countenaunce by Euria<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lus coming, whych was as next vnto him as Mecena to Detauian to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Emperour, loking aſide, ſayde doſte thou bren women on thys facion Eurialus? that woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſurely loueth the, and ones in maner as though he had enuied his loue, when hee came before Lucres houſe, he put Eurialus cappe ouer his eyne, thou ſhalte not ſe quod he that that thou loueſt, I wyl myſelfe vſe that ſyghte. Eurialus aunſwered, ſyr what meaneth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>? I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to doo wyth her, but take heede
<pb facs="tcp:13750:6"/>what ye doe, leaſte ye brynge ſuſpecte in them that bee here about vs. Eurialus was mounted vpon an hyghe rayned courier, with a ſmal head, whoſe ſhort bely and fayre heare cauſed him to ſhewe goodlye, wel breaſted, luſty, and courageous ſo that herynge the trumpet he could no where reaſt. he receiued the fury of the noiſe, his fayre mane honge vppon the ryghte ſyde, and the ground reſowned, beten with his fote, and not muche vnlyke him was his mayſter, when he had eſpyed Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres who beyng alone, as ſone as ſhe hadde ſene him, coulde neyther temper the flame, nor her ſelf ſo the vn happye Lucres did burne. In mene houſes dwelleth chaſtytie, and onely pouerty vſeth good affection, and chaſtitie that haunteth ſmal cotages, knoweth not the policies, for riche menne, who that haboundeth in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie lightlye deſyreth vnaccuſtomed thynges, fiers luſt, companyon to fortune hathe choſen delycate hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſtatelye mancions. Lucres, that oftentymes beholding Eurialus paſſynge by, myghte not aſſwage her ardaunte deſyre, buſely thinckynge to whome ſhe might her ſelfe diſcouer, for who that ſecreatlye bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, more greuouſly ſuffreth. Ther was amonge the ſeruauntes of her huſbande, one zoſias an Almayne olde and faythful to his mayſter: whome he had longe ſerued, verye honeſtlye, hym doth ſhe go vnto, truſting more to the nacyon than to the man.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Emperoure accompanyed wyth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye Noble menne, wente ſolacinge throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe the towne, and euen nowe did he paſſe by the houſe of Lucres who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe knew y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Eurialus was ther: Com hether quod ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:13750:7"/>zoſias I woulde ſpeke wyth the, loke heare oute of the wyndowe, where in the worlde is there anye youthe lyke thys, ſeeſt thou howe vpryghte and fayre ſpredde ſhoulders they haue? behoulde theyr buſhes and well kempte heares. Oh what faces, what fayre neckes.</p>
            <p>What noble hartes theyr countenaunces doth pretend thys is an other kynde of people than oure Countrye dothe brede, they ſeme Goddes or of heauenlye kynde. O that fortune hadde geuen me an huſbande of one of theeſe, yf myne eyene had not ſene them, I woulde neuer haue beleued the; yf thou hadde coulde me of them. Yet the fame is that the Almaynes excelleth all other people, and ſurely I beleue that the colde geueth to them greate whytenes, the countries ſo drawynge towarde the Northe. But dooeſt thou knowe anye of them. Yea many quod zoſias. Than quod Lucres, Eu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rialus the Franconien. dooſte thou knowe hym? Ye as myne owne ſelfe ſaythe zoſias, but whye doſte thou aſke? I ſhall tell the quod ſhee. I knowe it ſhal not bee diſcloſed, this hoope hath thy goodnes gyuen me.</p>
            <p>Amonge all them that are about the Emperour, none pleaſeth me lyke hym. In hym my mynde is meaned. I wotte not wyth what flames I burne, I canne ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgette hym, nor yet my ſelfe apeaſe, excepte that I maye make my ſelfe acquaynted with hym. Go therfore I beſeche the zoſias, ſeeke Eurialus, tell hym I loue hym, nothynge elles I deſyre of thee, and yet thys ſhalte thou not do in vayne. What is thys quod zoſias? ſhall I eyther do ſuch outrage, or ones thinke it Madame? ſhall I betraye my Mayſter? ſhall I now olde begynne too deceyue, whiche I haue hated in my youthe? Rather mooſte Noble Ladye of thys towne
<pb facs="tcp:13750:7"/>caſte fourth the wycked furoure oute of thy chaſte breſt folowe not thy cruell hoope, but quenche the fyre. Hee dothe not paynfullye put backe loue, that reſyſteth the fyrſte aſſautes, but hee that the ſweete yll flatterynge dothe nouryſhe, geueth hym to the bondage of a ryght harde and cruell mayſter nor whan hee woulde, maye not forſake the yocke, whyche yf thy huſbande ſhoulde knowe, halas vnder what facyon woulde he torments the? no loue can longe lye hyddene. Houlde thy peace quod Lucres, there is no fear at all, nothyng he fereth that feareth not death. I am content to ſuffer it what ſoeuer happeneth, what opinion dooſte thou houlde? Oh vnhappye quod zoſias, thou ſhalte ſhame thy houſe, and onelye of all thy kynne thou ſhalte bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultereſſe, thynkeſte, thynkeſt thou the deade can be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create. A thouſande eyne are aboute thee. Thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yf ſhe do accordynge, ſhall not ſuffer thy outrage to be preuye, not thy huſbande, not thy Couſyns, not thy maydens, ye, and thoughe thy ſeruauntes woulde holde theyr peace, the beſtes wold ſpeake it, the dogges the pooſtes, and the marble ſtones, and thoughe thou hyde all, thou can not hyde it from God, that ſeeth all. Vnderſtande that payne is preſente vnto a Gyltye thoughte, and the mynde, fylled wyth offence, feareth hym ſelfe. Faythe is denyed in greate crimes. Aſſwage I beſeeche the, the flames of wicked loue, feare too mengle ſtraunge makes in thy huſbandes bedde, I knowe quod ſhe it is accordinge as thou ſayſte, but the rage maketh me folow the worſe. My minde knoweth howe I fal hedlyng, but furour hath ouercom, and reig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth and ouer all my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ruleth loue. I am deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myned to folow the commaundemente of loue, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche
<pb facs="tcp:13750:8"/>muche alas haue I wreflied in vayne: yf thou haue pitie on me, carye my meſſage. Ful he auye was zoſias with this worde, and ſayde to her thus, for theſe hoore heares on my heade, by age, and for the faythfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice that I haue done vnto thy kynne, humblye I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſche the leue this furour and helpe thy ſelfe, a greate part of health, is to wyl to be healed. To whome ſayth Lucres all ſhame hathe not forſaken my mynde, I wyll obeye the zoſia, in the loue that canne not be hyd, onely the exchuyng of thys yll is by deathe to preuent the offence. zoſias affeared wyth thys ſayinge mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate quod hee my Ladye, the rage of thy vnbrideled mynde, tempere thy thoughte, nowe arte thou worthy lyfe, when thou iudgeſt thyſelfe worthye of deathe I am determined quod Lucres to dye. Collatinus wyfe the faute committed, venged wyth aſwearde. I more honeſtlye ſhall preuent it, I ſtudye but the kinde of my deathe, a corde, ſwearde, fall, or poyſone, ſhall reuenge chaſtitie, one of the eſe. I ſhall aſſaye, I wyll not ſuffer the quod zoſias, quod Lucres, who that determyneth to dye, can not be let. Perria, at the deathe of Brutus, whan weapon was taken from her, dyd eat hote coles. If the furoure bee ſoo frowarde in thy mynde quod zoſias, thy life is rather to be ſocoured, than thy fame, deceytfull is fame that to the ill, better and to the good worſer, is often geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let vs aſſay this Eurialus, and let vs intende to loue, the laboure ſhall be myne, and as I thincke, I ſhal brynge it to effecte.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith theeſe woordes the kindled thoughte hee enflamed, and gaue hoope to the doubtefull mynde, but hys mynde was not to dee as hee
<pb facs="tcp:13750:8"/>ſayde, he ſoughte to deferre the mynde of the woman, to aſwage the deſyre, as oftentymes tyme quencheth flames and ſufferannce healeth diſeaſes. zoſias went with fals truſte to dryue her forthe tyll the Emperoure ſhoulde departe, or ſhee ſhoulde chaunge her mynde, leaſt yf he hadde denyed it, another meſſanger ſhulde haue bene found, or els the woman ſhuld haue ſlayne her ſelfe, oftentimes therefore hee fayned him ſelfe to goo and comme, and that he reioyced in her loue, and ſought a conuenient time that they mighte talke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſometime that he could not ſpeke with him, ſome time he ſoughte to be ſente oute of the towne, and tyll his retourne deferred her glad dayes, ſo, manye dayes he dyd feede the ſycke mynde, and becauſe he ſhoulde not lye in all thynges, once onelye he brake vnto Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alus, ſayinge. O how thou art here beloued, yet whan he aſked what that mente, he anſwered not. But Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialus, ſtryken with the ſecret dart of Cupido, gaue no reſt nor ſleape to hys lymmes, the fyre ſo crepte in hys vaynes and vtterlye waſted his marye: yet knewe he not zoſia, nor thoughte him to be the meſſenger of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres, ſo haue we all leſſe hope then deſyre. He whan he ſawe him ſelfe burne, a great while with this wiſdom wondered, and vnder thys facyon oftentymes blamed hym ſelfe. Lo Eurialus, thou knoweſt what the rage of loue is, longe playntes, and ſhorte laughters, fewe ioyes, and manye dreades, alwayes hee dyeth, and is neuer deade that loueth. What dooſte thou meddle in vayne: at laſt quod he, all for noughte. O wretch, whye ſtryue I agaynſt loue? May not I do that Iulius that Alexander, that Hanybal dyd? and theſe were worthye
<pb facs="tcp:13750:9"/>warryoures. Loke deſydes vpon Pocies, Vngyll dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vp by a roape, honge in the mydwaye to the wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, truſtynge to haue enbraced hys loue. If anye man wyll excuſe the Poet, as a folower of a more diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute lyfe, what ſhall we ſaye of Philoſophers, maiſtres of learning, and rulers of good lyuyng. A woman dyd ryde Ariſtotle lyke a horſe, and ruled him wyth a bridle and ſpurred hym. It is not true that is ſayde comonly honoure and loue accorde not together. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roures power is equall with the goodes, and who is a greater louer then hee? They ſaye that Hercules that was ſtrongeſt of all menne, and of the race of Goddes the diſroyle of the lyon and hys quyuere layde a parte, tooke in hande a rocke, and trymmed rynges for hys fyngers, and ſette in order his rudde buſſhe, and wyth his hande, wherewyth he wonted too carye a mace, by tyrlynge of a ſpyndell he drewe a threde, it is a natural paſſyon. Byrdes are brent wyth thys fyre. The turtull and the doue doth loue. What ſhal I ſaye of beaſtes? The horſe meueth battel forloue. The fearfull hearte ſeketh to fyght, and by beleuinge ſheweth his furoure The fiers Tegre, and the cruell Boore, wheftyng hys teathe, doth vſe it. And the Lions of Libia ſet vp theyr roughe manes, whan loue moueth. The monſtures of the ſea do fele this heate, nothynge is free, ne nothing vnto loue denyed. Hate gyueth place vnto it. If ſtyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the fyers flames of youth, and vnto weryage itre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh the dead heate, and ſtriketh the breſtes of may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens with a brennynge fyre. Whye then doo I ſtryue agaynſt the lawes of loue? Loue ouercommeth all thynge, and let vs gyue place vnto hym: ¶ Whan theſe thynges were concluded, he ſeeketh a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> too
<pb facs="tcp:13750:9"/>whome he myghte take her letters to carye to her. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus was his faythefull felowe, and vnderſtode muche in ſuche matters. He taketh the buſynes in hande, and hyreth a woman to whome the letters were taken, wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten as foloweth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>¶ Eurialus vnto Lucres.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wolde ſende the greatynge and healthe with my letters yf I had any my ſelf, but ſurelye, bothe of my healthe and lyfe, the hope hangeth in my handes. More than myſelfe I loue thee, and I weene it is not vnknowne vnto thee, my face ofte moyſted wyth teares, maye ſhewe token of my woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded breaſte, and the ſyghtes whyche in thy preſence I haue caſte fourthe. Take it wel I beſeche the that I diſcouere me vnto the, thy beautye hathe takenne me and the grace of godlye hede, wherein thou paſſeſt all othere, houldeth me, what loue mente vnto nowe I neuer knewe, but thou haſte ſubdued mee too thy power of thy deſyre, longe dyde I ſtryue (I confeſſe) to eſcape ſo violente a mayſter, but thy bryghtneſſe hathe ouercome myne endeuoure, the beamys of thine eyne paſſynge the ſonne, hathe ouer come me. I am takenne and am noo moore myne owne, the vſe of meate and drincke thou takeſt fro me, contynually I the loue, the I deſyre, the I call, thee I awayte, thee I thincke on, the I truſte in, and wyth thee I delyte mee, thyne is my mynde, and with the it is hole. Thou onlye mayſte ſaue me, thou onelye mayſte leſe me, the one of theeſe chuſe, and what thou intendeſt, wryte it vnto me. Bee no more harde in thy wordes in anſwerynge me, than thou was wyth thyne eyne in bynedynge me. It is noo
<pb facs="tcp:13750:10"/>greate thynge that I aſke. To ſpeake conuenyentlye wyth the I aſke, this onelye deſyreth my letters. That that I wryte, I may ſay afore the, this if thou graunte me, I lyue, and well happe I lyue, yf not thou ſſeeſt my harte that the more then me loueth. I recommend me vnto thy good grace, and to the truſte that I haue in the. And thus fare well the delyte and reſydue of my lyfe.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heeſe letters ſealed, when the woman hadde receyued, haſtelye ſhe wente vnto Lucres, and fyne dynge her alone, ſaide vnto her thus. The mooſte Noble of the Emperoures Courte, thy louer ſendeth the theeſe letters, and prayeth the inſtantlye to take him vnto thy grace. Thys woman was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a baude, and that knewe Lucres and tooke it verye diſpleaſauntlye to haue a naughtye womanne ſente vnto her, and to her ſhee ſayde, what madneſſe hathe meued the to come to my preſence? arte thou ſo boulde to entre the houſes of noble menn? dareſt thou prouoke greate ladyes to violate ſacred mariage? ſka<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t canne I houlde my handes from thy eare? bryngeſt thou letters vnto me? ſpeakeſt thou vnto me? dareſt thou loke me in mi face? If I regarded not more what becommeth me, thanne what thou deſerueſt, I ſhulde ſo order the that thou ſhouldeſt after thys daye neuer carye more letters of loue, entre out of my ſyghte abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minable queane, and take thy letters wyth the, yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gyue them me, that I maye caſte them in the fyre and ſnatchynge the paper from her, tare it in peaces and trode vnder her fete, ſpyttynge at it, caſte it in the aſſhes ſo ſhoulde thy ſelfe be punyſhed, baud quod ſhe more worthye the fyre, than thy lyfe pycke the hence
<pb facs="tcp:13750:10"/>ſhortlye leaſte that my huſbande, finedynge the heare gyue the that that I remytte vnto the, and whyle thou lyueſt, neuer come in my ſyghte. Another would haue bene afrayd, but ſhe wel acquaynted with the maners of women, thoughte to her ſelfe, nowe wouldeſt thou mooſte, when thou ſheweſt mooſte the contrarye, and ſayde vnto her forgeue me madame, I thoughte I had not done a myſſe, and that it ſhoulde haue ſtande wyth thy pleaſure, if it be otherwyſe, pardone myne igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, if thou wylte not that I retourne vnto the, I ſhall obey thy commaundemente, but take thou heede what a louer thou forſakeſt, and with theeſe woordes departed from her, and when ſhe hadde founde Euria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus: be of good conforte quod ſhe thou louer, the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loueth more the, then ſhee is loued, but nowe it is was no tyme to wryte vnto the, I founde her ſad, but whan I named the, and gaue her thy letters, ſhe made good countenaunce, and kyſſed the paper a thouſand tymes doubte not, thou ſhalte ſhortlye haue an aunſweare, and thus the olde woman departynge, ſhee was well ware no more to be founde leaſte ſhe hadde ſuffred for her lyinge. ☞ Truelye Lucres, after the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was departed ſoughte vp the peeces of the lettre, and ſette eche in theyre place, and ioyned ſoo the torne woordes, that ſhee made it legeable whyche when ſhee hadde redde it a thouſande tymes, a thouſande tymes ſhe kyſſed it, and at the laſte wrapped it in a fayre nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyn, and putte it amonge her Iuels, and remembryng nowe thys woorde, nowe that woorde, continuallye ſhee ſooked in more loue, and determyned too wryte to Eurialus, and ſente her lettere on thys faſhyonen, dyted.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13750:11"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>¶ Lucres to Euriales.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eurialus leaue to hope, after that thou canſte not attayne, leue to bere me with thy letters and meſſangers, thyncke not that I am of that ſorte that ſell them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, I am not ſhe that thou takeſt me for nor vnto whome thou ſhouldeſt ſende a bawde, ſeeke for thy luſte anothere. No affeccione but chaſtitie ſhall folowe, wyth othere do as the liketh, but of me aſke nothynge, for bee thou ſure I am vnmeete for the. Farewel. This letter (thoughe it ſemed vnto Eurialus very harde, and contrary to the womannes woordes) yet dyd ſhewe hym the redye waye howe too ſende hys letters, for he doubted not to truſte, whome ſhe truſted, but the ignoraunce of the Italien toungue combred hym, therfore wyth buſye ſtudye he learned it and becauſe loue made him diligent, he was in ſhorte whyle cunnynge, and hymſelfe alone endited his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whyche afore he was wonte to borowe, whan hee ſhulde wryte anye thynge in Italien. He aunſwered than to Lucres, that ſhe ſhuld not be dyſpleaſed wyth hym, becauſe he ſente an vnhoneſt womanne to her, ſythen hee as a ſtraunger knewe it not, and coulde vſe none other meſſangere. The cauſe of hys ſendyng was hys loue, deſiringe noo diſhoneſtye, hee beleued her verye honeſte and chaſte, and ſo muche more to bee beloued, and that vnhoneſt womenne, and ouer lybe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of theyr honoure he dydde not onelye not loue: but alſo greatlye hate, for chaſtitye, loſte, nothynge is in a womanne to be prayſed, for beautye is a delectable ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and a frayle, and noughte to be eſtemed wythoute
<pb facs="tcp:13750:11"/>honeſtye, and that ſhee that honeſtye wynneth wyth beauty, paſſeth in bothe giftes, and that therfore he did honoure her, and onlye he deſyred to ſpeake wyth her, that he myght by his wordes declare hys mynd, that he coulde not by his letters. With ſuche manere of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hee ſente her a tokene, not onelye ryche in value, but excellent in the workmanſhyp.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>¶ To theſe letters Lucres thus anſwered.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue receyued thy letters, nor it is not the womanne nowe I blame the for. That thou loueſt me I eſteame not greatelye, for thou arte neither alone, nor the fyrſte whome they ſaye my beautye hathe deceyued. Manye haue loued me, and do loue me, but thy laboure as well as theyres ſhalbe in vayne. I neyther can nor wyll talke wyth the and excepte thou were a ſwalowe thou canſte not fynd me alone. The houſes be byghe, and the gates be kept. I haue takene thy token for that the facione pleaſeth me, but becauſe I wyll nothynge of thyne for nought, and that it ſhal not be as a tokene of loue, I ſende the rynge, whyche my huſbande gaue my mothere, that it maye be to the as pryce of thy Iuels for it is of no leſſe value than thy gyfte. Farewell.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O theſe letters Eurialus replied. Great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort were thy letters vnto me that thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playneſt no more of the womane. But that thou ſetteſt thy loue ſo lyghte, greueth me ſore for though many do loue the, none of theyr loue is ſo feruent as myne, but thou beleueſt it not, for that I
<pb facs="tcp:13750:12"/>may not ſpeke with the, but yf I myghte, thou ſhuldeſt not wey it ſo lyght. Would to God as thou ſayeſt, that I myghte be a ſwalow, ye, or a leſſe thynge, that thou myghte not ſhytte thy wyndowe agaynſte me, but my moſt grefe is not that thou can not, but that thou wylt not. Ah my Lucres, what meaneth that thou wylt not, yf thou myghte woldeſt thou not ſpeake with me that am a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l thyne? and that nought deſyreth ſo muche as to pleaſe the. If thou bydde me goo into the fyre, I ſhall ſoner obey then thou ſhalte commaunde. Sende me worde I beſeche the, that yf thou mighte thy wyll were good. Geue me not death with thy wordes, that mayſte gyue lyfe vnto me with thyne eyene. If thou wylte not ſpeke wyth me becauſe thou maiſte not, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente, but chaunge that woorde I praye the that ſayeſt my laboure ſhall be in vayne, God forbyd in the ſuche crueltye. Be I beſeche the more genteller to thy verye louer, yf thou continue ſo, thou ſhalte ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee me, and bee thou ſure, ſoner thou with a worde, then another wyth aſworde. I aſke, thou haſt none excuſe, no man canne forbyd the that, ſaye thou loueſt me, and I am happye that my tokene remayneth wyth the, howe ſoeuer it be I am glad of it, it ſhall ſometime remember the of my loue, but it was to ſimple, and that that I ſend the now is leſſe, but refuſe not thou that thy louer ſendeth the, I ſhal haue out of my country dayly better when they come, thou ſhalt not lacke them. Thy rynge ſhal neuer part from my fynger, and in ſtede of the I ſhal moyſt it wyth continual kyſſes. Farewel my health, and in that thou maye healpe me.</p>
                  <p>¶ At the laſt after many wrytings and anſweres Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres ſent him ſuch a letter.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13750:12"/>
                  <head>¶ Lucres to Eurialus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wolde fayne Eurialus do the pleaſure, and as thou deſyreſt, rewarde the with my loue, for that aſketh thy Nobleneſſe, and thy condycyons deſerueth it, that thou ſhuldeſt not loue in vayne, beſides thy beauty and goodlye face but it is not for me to loue the. I knowe my ſelfe, if I begyn to loue I ſhall neyther keepe meaſure nor rule. Thou canſte not longe be heare, and yf I fall vnto the, I canne not lacke the, thou wouldeſt not take me wyth thee and I ſurelye woulde not longe tarye behynde the. Manye examples do meue to refuſe a ſtraungers loue. Iaſon that wanne the golden flece by Mede as councel, forſoke her. Theſe us had bene caſt to the Minaturs had not the councel of Adriana healped him, yet dyd he leue her behinde him in an Ilande. What became on the vnhappye Dido. that receyued the wanderyng Ene as Was not her loue her deathe? I knowe what pearyll it is to receyue a ſtraungers loue, nor I wyl not put me into ſuche haſardes. You menne are of more ſtronger mynde, and ſoner can quenche the fyre. A womanne whan ſhe begynneth to loue, onelye by deathe maketh an ende. Women rage, they doe not loue, and excepte they be aunſwered wyth loue, nothynge is more terry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, after the fyre bee kyndled, we neyther regard fame nor lyfe. The onelye remeadye is the obtaynyng of the louer, for that that we mooſte lacke, we mooſte deſyre Nor we feare no daunger for oure appetites. I than ſynce am maryed, and vnto a noble ryche man, am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyned too exclude all loues, and ſpecyallye thyne, which can not be contynual leaſt I be noted as Philis
<pb facs="tcp:13750:13"/>or Sapho. Therefore I deſyre the no more to aſke my loue, and lytle by lyttle to aſſwage and quenche thyne, for it is more eaſy to menne then to women, nor thou yf thou loue me, as thou ſayeſt, woldeſt not deſire that that ſhoulde be my deſtruccion. For thy token I ſende the a croſſe of golde, ſette with pearles, which thoughe it be lytle, is of ſome value. Farewel.</p>
                  <p>¶ Eurialus to this letter helde not hys peace, but as he was with the newe wrytynge kyndeled, ſo tooke he the penne in hande, and vnder thys forme folowynge endyted a letter.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>¶ Eurialus vnto Lucres.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onour and helth be vnto my deare harte Lucres ſhe that geueth me helth with her letters, though they be medled ſomewhat with galle, yet I truſte when thou haſte heard myne thou ſhalt withdraw it. Thy letters are come to my hands ſealed, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I haue red oftentymes and kyſſed as oft. But it ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth to me ane another thyng than thy mynde wolde. Thou deſireſt me to leue to loue, becauſe it is not mete for the to folow a ſtraungers loue, bryngyng examples of ſuch that hathe bene ſo deceiued (ſo eloquently) that I muſt rather wonder of the, then forget the. Who would then leaue to loue, when he ſeeth ſuche wit and learning in his mayſtres? Yf thou woldeſt haue ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my loue thou ſhuldeſt not haue ſhewed thine elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, for that it is not too quenche the fyre, but too make it rather flame, the more I reade it, the more I burned, ſeyng thy beauty and honeſty ſo ioyned, wyth learning but it is in vayne to deſyre me to leue to loue
<pb facs="tcp:13750:13"/>the. Deſyre the hylles too bee come playne, and the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers to retourne into the ſprynges. For aſwell maye I leaue to loue, as the ſonne hys courſe. If the hyghe mountaines maye wante ſnowes, or the ſea fiſhes, yf the foreſtes maye wante Dere, then maye Eurialus forget the. Men are not ſo prone as thou weneſt Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres, to quenche theyr deſires, for that that thou geueſt vnto oure kynde, men do aſcribe it vnto youres, but I wyll not vndertake that to debate, to that muſt I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere whiche toucheth me neare, for the deceytes of other, thou bryngeſt in examples whereby thou wylte not rewarde me with thy loue. But more are too be brought my Lucres, whome womenne hath deceyued Troylus by Creſyde. Deiphus by Helena. And Circes by her enchauncementes deceyued her louers, But it were not accordynge, by the dedes of a fewe, to iudge al the reſt. Shuldeſt thou for a certayne yll man abhorre and accuſe all menne? Or I for manye yll wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, hate all the reſt? nay, rather lette vs take other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, as was of Anthonius and Cleopatra, and of other whome the ſhortnes of my letters letteth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herce, but it is red that the Grekes, retournynge from Troy, haue bene holden by ſtraungers loues, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue come to their countries, but taried wyth their loues, contente rather too wante theyr frendes, theyre houſes, theyre reygnes, and othere deare thynges of theyr countrye, than to forſake theyr Ladyes. Thys I beſeche the my Lucres, remember and note thoſe few thinges that be agaynſte oure loue. So do I loue the, to loue the alwayes, and euer to bee thyne. Nor call me no ſtraunger, I pray the, for I am rathere of thys con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye, than he that is borne heare, ſythens hee is but by
<pb facs="tcp:13750:14"/>chaunce and I by myne owne choyſe, no countrye is myne, but where thou arte. And thoughe I departe at anye tyme, my retourne ſhall be ſhorte, nor I ſhall not retourne at all into my country, but too ſette ordere in my buſyneſſes, that I maye dwell longe with thee, wherefore, occaſyon maye be found ſone inough. The Emperour hath much to do in theſe parties the charge wherof I wyl ſue to haue, ſometime as ambaſſatoure, ſometyme as commyſſyoner, and he muſt haue a lieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunt in Strucia, and that wyll I optayne. Doubte not my delyte, my hearte, and my only truſt. If I may lyue yet pitye thy louer that melteth lyke ſnowe afore the. Sone conſyder my trauayles, and nowe at laſt ſet an ende to my tormentes, whye punyſheſt thou me ſo longe I wonder of my ſelfe, howe I haue ſuffered ſo many euyles, howe I haue waked ſo manye nyghtes, howe I haue forborne my mefe and my drynke ſo long beholde howe lene I am, and howe pale, a ſmall thyng is it that holdeth the lyfe wythin my bodye, yf I hadde ſlayne thy Parentes or thy chyldren, thou couldeſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe me no ſorer, yf thou ſo handle me for that I loue the, what ſhalt thou do to them that haue offended the Ah my Lucres, my Ladye, my healthe, and my ſocoure take me vnto thy grace, and at laſte wryte vnto mee that I am thy beloued, nothynge I woulde elſſe, but that I myghte ſaye I am thy Seruaunte. Pardye boothe Kynges and Emperoures loue theyr faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruauntes, nor the Goddes diſdayne not to know them that loueth theym. Farewell my truſte and my dreade.</p>
                  <p>¶ Lyke as a towre craked wythinne, ſowndynge outwarde impreuyble, yf a piece of ordynaunce bee
<pb facs="tcp:13750:14"/>ſhotte againſt it, furthwith it rente in pieces: So was Lucres ouercome with Eurialus wordes, for after ſhe had perceiued the diligence of the louer, her diſſembled loue ſhe declared with ſuche letters.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>¶ Lucres to Eurialus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Maye no more Eurialus reſyſte thy requeſtes, nor longer wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold my loue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the. I am ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, vnhappye womane, by thy letters, whiche if thou obſerueſt not, accordynge to thy wryting, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt be of al periured traitours, the worſt. It is eaſy to deceyue a woman, but ſo much, is it the more ſhameful, now that I am come into thy loue, and as a woman, can conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but little, thou that art a man, take charge bothe of thy ſelfe and of me. Thyne I am, and thy faythe I fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and thyne wold I not be, except it were for euer. Fare well the ſtaye and leader of my lyfe. ¶ After thys were manye letters wrytten on bothe parties, and Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialus wrote not ſoo vehementlye, as Lucres dyd anſwere feruently, and that hadde bothe one deſyre of their metinge, but it ſeamed hearde, and almooſte im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, ſithens the eyne of euerye bodye dyd behoulde Lucres, whyche neuer went forthe alone, nor wanted a keper, Nor Argus neuer kepte Iunos Cowe ſo dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlye as Menelaus cauſed Lucres to be kept This vice is of propertye to the Italyens, too ſhutte vp theyr wyues as theyr treaſoure and on my fayth (to my iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente) too lyttle purpoſe, for the mooſte parte of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="tcp:13750:15"/>be of thys ſorte, that mooſte they deſire, that moſt to them is denyed, and when thou wouldeſt, they wyll not, and when thou wouldeſt not, they woulde, and yf they haue the brydell at lybertye, leſſe they offende ſoo that it is as eaſye to kepe a woman agaynſte her wyll as a ſtocke of flyes in the heate of the ſonne, excepte ſhe be of her ſelfe chaſte. In vayne dothe the huſbande ſet kepers ouer her, for who ſhal kepe thoſe keepers. She is craftye, and at them lyghtlye ſhee begynneth and whan ſhe taketh a fantaſye, ſhe is vnreaſonable, and like an vnbrideled mule, ¶ Lucres hath a brother in lawe hee caryed her letters, and was of Councell in her loue wyth hym ſhee had appoynted to ſhutte pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelye Eurialus in hys houſe, and hee dwelled wythin hys ſtepmother, that was Lucres mother, whome Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres dyd oftentimes viſite, and was alſo of her of tentymes vyſyted, for they dwelte not farre a ſonder. Nowe thys was the order of it, Eurialus ſhoulde bee ſhut in the parlere, and after the mother was gonne to the churche, Lucres ſhould come as it were to ſpeke wyth her, and not finedyng her, ſhulde tarye for her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne, in the meane tyme ſhee ſhoulde be wyth Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialus, this ſhoulde bee within two dayes, but theeſe two dayes were two yeares to the louers for too them that hope well, the houres be longe, and too them that truſt lytle, they be as ſhorte, but fortune folowed not theyr deſyres. The mother myſtruſted, and at that day whan ſhe went forth, ſhut her ſon in lawe oute, whiche broughte to Eurialus the heauy newes, to whome the diſpleaſoure was no leſſe, then too Lucres, whyche when he ſawe her craft perceyued, let vs go quod ſhee another waye to werke, yet ſhall not my mother lette
<pb facs="tcp:13750:15"/>my appetyte. One Pandalus was her huſbandes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyn, whome ſhe had alſo made preuy of her ſecreates, for the flamynge mynde myght no where reſte. She aduertyſed Eurialus to ſpeke wyth hym, for hee was truſty, and coulde fynde well a meane for their meting but Eurialus thought it not ſure to truſte hym, whome he ſawe alway wyth hym. Menelaus fearyng thereby deceyte. In takynge deliberatyon, hee was ſente by the Emperoure to Rome, to determyne with the Pope for hys Coronacyon, whyche was bothe vnto hym and her greuous, but it muſte be obeyed, ſo was hys Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neye two monethes longe. In the meane tyme Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres kepte here houſe, ſhutte vp her wyndowes, putte on ſadde apparell, and no where wente ſhee fourthe, euery body marueled, and knew not the cauſe, ſythen the wyndowes of the towne ſhewed theim ſelfe, and they of the houſe thoughte theim ſelfe in darckeneſſe, as though they hadde wanted the ſonne, ſeynge her often on her bedde, and neuer merye, thought it ſycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſought all remedies that myghte bee, but ſhe neuer neyther laught nor came oute of her chambere, tyll tyme ſhe knewe that Eurialus was comme to the preſence of the Emperoure, for than, as waked oute of a ſteape, ſhe layde aparte her ſad clothes, and dreſſed wyth her former gorge ouſnes, opened her wyndowes gladlye lokynge for hym, whome whan the Emperour ſaw, deny no more quod he Eurialus, the mater is per ceyued, neuer man in thy abſence myghte ſee Lucres nowe that thou art come, we maye ſe the bryghte mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, what meaſure is in loue? it can not be cloked nor hydden with hemmes. ¶ Ye mocke ſyr quod Euri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alus, and fynde your laughter at mee, I knowe not
<pb facs="tcp:13750:16"/>what it meaneth, the nayhynge of youre horſes hathe perauenture wakened her, and whan he hadde ſayde, preuelye he behelde Lucres and fyxed faſt hys eyne in heres, and that was theyr fyrſt ſalutacion after hys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne. Shortlye after Niſus Eurialus truſty frende diligently purſuyng his frendes cauſe, founde a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, whyche behynde Menelaus houſe had a wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe towarde Lucres chambre. Hee maketh the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerner hys frende, and when he hadde voyde the place bryngeth thyder Eurialus, ſayinge; oute of thys wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe mayſte thou ſpeke with Lucres, betwyxte booth houſes was a darke canel, whyche no manne came to deuydynge Lucres wyndow from the chambre, by the ſpace of thre elles. Here ſat the louer awaytynge yf by, chaunce he myghte ſee her and hee was not deceyued, for at laſte ſhe came to the wyndowe, and lokyng hers and there, what doſt thou quod Eurialus, the nouryſe of my lyefe, whether tourneſt thou thyne eyne, my dere hart? hyther tourne them I praye the, ſoke hether my healthe, beholde thyne Eurialus is here, I my ſelfe am here. Arte thou there quod Lucres? Oh my Euria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, now may I ſpeke with the, and wold god I might embrace the. It ſhal not nede no greate buſynes quod Eurialus, I ſhall ſette to a ladder, opene thy chamber, to longe haue we differred the inioinyng of oure loue Beware of that quod ſhe my Eurialus yf thou loue, mi lyfe, he are is a wyndowe on the ryghte hande, and a verye yll neyghboure, and the Tauerner is not too be truſted, that for a lyttle monye wolde perauenture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traye bothe the and me, but lette vs worcke otherwyſe it is inough yf heare we may talke together. But thys is death to me ſayth Eurialus, wythoute I myghte in
<pb facs="tcp:13750:16"/>myne armes embrace the. In thys place did they taſke longe, and at the laſte reached eache to other tokens vppon a reade, and Eurialus was no more lyberall in hys gyftes, then Lucres was. zoſias perceyued the crafte, and ſayde to hym ſelfe. In vayne do I reſyſte the mynde of the louers, and except I prouide wyſely, my mayſtres is vndon, and the houſe ſhamed for euer of bothe theeſe ylles, it is beſt too wythſtande the one, my mayſtres loueth, yf it be ſecrete, it maketh no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſhe is blynde for loue and ſeeth not well what ſhee doeth. If chaſtitye can not be kepte, it is ynoughe to hyde the noyſe, leaſte the hole houſe bee ſlaundered, or leaſte there be anye murdre done, ſurelye I wyll go to her, and healpe her, whyle I myghte I dyd wythſtand that no offence ſhulde be done, and becauſe I myghte not, it is nowe my part too hyde that that needes wyll be, leaſte it be knowne. Loue is an vniuerſall rayng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng miſchief, nor none ther is not enfected with this ſicknes, and he is iudged mooſte chaſte that is mooſte ſecrete. And thus thynkynge wyth hym ſelfe, Lucres came oute of her chambre, and zoſias meatynge her, ſayde thus. What meaneth it that thou deuyſeſt wyth me no more of thy loue? and neuertheles Eurialus is beloued of the, take heede whome thou truſteſt. The fyrſte poynt of wyſdome is, not to loue at al. The nexte that at the leaſt it be ſecrete, and thou alone wythoute a meſſanger, canſt not do it. In what truſt thou mayſt putte me in, by longe tyme thou haſte learned, yf thou wylt truſt me, tell me, for all my mooſte care is leſt this loue, yf it bee knowne, thou ſhalt ſuffere, and thy huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande mooſte of all. To thys aunſwered Lucres, it is as thou ſayeſt zoſias, and I truſte the muche, but mee
<pb facs="tcp:13750:17"/>thoughte I wote not howe negligente, and agaynſte my deſyre. Nowe that thou offereſt thy ſelfe, I wyll vſe thy diligence, and I feare not too be deceyued of the. Thou knoweſt howe I burne, and longe I maye not endure thys flambe, healpe me that we maye be together, Eurialus for loue languyſſheth, and I dye. Nothynge is to vs worſe, than to lette oure appetytes, yf we may ones mete together, oure loue ſhall be more temperate, and it ſhall well be hydde. God than and ſhewe Eurialus the onelye waye too come to me, yf he wyll within theſe foure dayes whan the vyllaynes bryng in whete diſguyſe hym lyke a portour, and clothe hym ſelfe in ſackeclothe, and carye the corne in too the garner. Thou knoweſt my chambre hath a backe dore by the lader, tell all vnto Eurialus, and I ſhall wayte for hym and whan tyme is, I ſhal be alone in my cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, and whan he is alone, let hym put opene the doore and come into me. zoſias thoughe it were a hyghe mater fearynge a worſe, taketh in hand the buſynes, and fyndyng Eurialus, appoynteth wyth hym the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of euery thynge, whych he as lyght thynges glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acepteth, and maketh hym redy to this meſſege, and noughte playneth but of longe aboade. O inſenſyble breſt of a louer. O blynde thoughte. O hardye mynde and vnfearful hert. What is ſo vnacceſſyble that thou thynkeſt not open ynough? what waye ſo ſharpe that the ſemeth not playne? what is ſo cloſe that is not too be vncloſed? thou ſetteſt lyght al daungers, thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt nothynge to harde, vayne is the gelouſye of huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes agaynſt the, neyther lawe nor feare doth hold the, to no ſhame arte thou ſubiecte, to the all laboures is but playe. Oh loue, ſubduer of all thynge, a noble
<pb facs="tcp:13750:17"/>man, derely beloued with the Emperour, riche, of good age, well lerned and of greate witte, thou bringeſt in that caſe, that purple layd a part, he clothes him ſelf in ſacke clothe, he diſſembleth hys owne face, and of a ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter, he is becomen a ſeruante and he that deliciouſlye hath bene nouryſhed, now dreſſeth his ſholders for the burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and letteth hym ſelf to hyre for a common portour Oh maruelouſe thyng and almoſte vncredible, to ſee a man, in other thynges a graue counceller, among the company of boyſtrous portoures, preſſynge hym ſelfe amonge ſuche raſkall people, who wyl ſeeke a greater charge? Thys ſame it is that Ouide meaneth in hys tranſformacyons, whan he telleth how wemen becam beaſtes, ſtones, or trees. That ſame is it that the noble Poete Virgyll meaneth whan he telleth howe Circes enchaunted her louers into beaſtes, for ſo fareth it by loue, ſo is the mynde of man therby chaunged, that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle he differreth from a be aſt.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He morning forſaking the golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bed of Titan, reduced the diſired day, and ſhortlie the ſonne decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the colour of eche thinge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced the wayter Eurialus, that thought him the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> happy and fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, when hee ſawe hym ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the vyle portours, ſo goeth he furthe into the houſe of Lucres, charged hym ſelfe wyth whete and ſettinge it in the garner, deſcended laſt of the companye, and as he was taughte, the doore of the chambre then was putte too, he thruſt open, and went in, and ſhuttynge the dore after hym, hee founde
<pb facs="tcp:13750:18"/>Lucres about ſylkworcke and comynge towarde her, god ſpede quod he my dere harte and the onlye healpe and hoope of my lyfe, Lucres, thoughe ſhee hadde ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted thys matter, at the fyrſte ſighte, was ſomwhat abaſhed, and thoughte it hadde beene rather a ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, than her louer Eurialus for ſhee coulde not well beleue that ſuche a manne as he wolde venture ſuche bylles but afterwarde in kyſſynge, and embracynge ſhe knew well Eurialus, and ſayd. Art thou here quod ſhe pore portoure, arte thou here myne owne Eurialus and than ſhee ſtraynynge hym ſtrayter. lookynge in hys face, began hyr wordes agayne thus Alas quod ſhe my deare hearte Eurialus, what daunger haſte thou aduentured, what ſhall I ſaye nowe, I perceyue I am mooſte deare vnto thee, I haue made proofe of thy loue, and thou ſhalte neuer fynde mee noone othere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe vnto the. God ſende vs onlye good lucke, in oure loue, and whyle the ſpyryte ſhall rule my lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, noone ſhall bee before thee wyth Lucres, noo. Not my huſbande yf I cal hym ryghte: My huſbande that was geuen mee agaynſte my wyll, whereto my mynde neuer conſented. But nowe I beſeche the my Eurialus, caſt away thys ſacke clothe, and ſhewe thee vnto me as thou arte put away this porters garmente and laye awaye theſe ropes. Lette me ſe my Eurialus, than he caſt of the fylthy apparel, and ſhone al in golde and purpull, and began to entende buſely to the offyce of loue, whanne zoſias ſcrapynge at thee doore, ſayde take hede ye louers, Menelaus ſeekynge I wote not what, cometh hyder hide all thynge preuelye for out, ye can not ſcape. Than quod Lucres there is by the bed a darke cloſette where bee Iuels, thou wotteſt what I
<pb facs="tcp:13750:18"/>wrote vnto the, yf my huſbande came in, whyle thou were wyth me, goo thou thythere, there thou mayſt be ſure in the derke, and neyther ſtyrre nor ſpytte, Euria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus beynge in doubte what he ſhould doo, folowed the womans byddynge ſhe ſette open the dore and wente to her worke. Then came Menelaus, and one Bertus a ſcryuener wyth hym, to ſeeke thynges that belonged to the common weale, whiche when they were not in diuers boxes found, they are perauenture quod Mene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laus in the cloſet. Go Lucres, and fetch a lyghte for to ſeke here. With this woord, Eurialus was ſore afraid and beganne ſtrayght to hate Lucres, and to hym ſelf ſayd. Ah foole that I am. Who cauſed me too comme hether, but myne owne lyghteneſſe. I am takenne, I am aſhamed, I ſhall leaſe the Emperoures fauoure, what for fauour? I wold God my lyfe were ſafe. Howe ſhall I ſcape a lyue? I am ſure too dye. Oh vayne, and of all fooles mooſte folyſhe, I am fallen intoo theeſe breres wylfullye, to what purpoſe is thee enioyinge of loue, yf it be bought ſoo deare? the pleaſures be ſhorte and the doloures infinite. Oh yf we woulde endure, theſe thynges for heauen, it is a maruelous folyſhnes of men that forſaketh lyghte laboures, for longe ioyes and for loue, whoſe ioyes be comparable to ſmoke, wee putte our ſelfes into extreme daungers, Loo, myſelfe nowe ſhall I bee a tale and example too euerye bodye, and knowe not what ende ſhall becomme of it, if anye good Saynte woulde healpe me hence, neuer agayne ſhall ſuche laboure deceyue. O good Lorde healpe mee hence, and pardon my youthe. Remember not myne ignoraunces, but ſaue me to repente me of thys faute. She hath not loued me, but as a dere hathe takene me
<pb facs="tcp:13750:19"/>in the net, my day is come, no manne may healpe me, but thou good Lorde. Oft haue I hearde the deceytes of women, and I coulde not eſchew it yf I eſcape now there ſhall neuer no crafte of women deceyue me. But Lucres was all yll combred, that feared as muche hys healthe as her owne, and as womens wyttes is more redye than mannes, in ſodeyne peryls, hadde found a remedy. Come hether quod ſhe huſband, here is a caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket in this wyndowe, wherein I haue ſene you put dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers thinges of charge let vs ſe yf the wrytyng be thee and runnynge as it were to opene it, ouerthrewe yt into the ſtrete, and as it had bene bechaunce, alas quod ſhe, come hether, huſbande leaſte we leſe anye thynge the caſket is fallen out of the windowe, go quyckelye, leaſt anye Iewels or wrytynges fall oute, go goo for goddes ſake, why tary ye? I wyll looke oute that noo man take nothynge. Se the deſceyte of the womanne nowe truſte them hardely, no man is ſo circumſpecte, that can not be deceyued, he was neuer kyndlye decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued whome hys wyfe neuer aſſayed to deceyue, we are ofte more fortunate then wyſe. Menelaus and Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus abaſſhed with this ſame ranne bothe haſtely into the ſtrete, the houſe was high after the Italian facion and manye ſteppes downe. Whereby Eurialus hadde ſpace to chaunge and putte himſelfe by her councell in to another darcke corner. They when they had gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the wrytinges and the iewels, becauſe they found not that that they ſoughte, wente intoo the cloſette, where they founde it, and ſo byddynge her farewel, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and ſhe barred the dore. Come forthe quod ſhee Eurialus come forthe my dere hart, and the ſumme of my ioyes, come the well of my delytes, and ſprynge of
<pb facs="tcp:13750:19"/>my gladnes, all thynge is ſure, we may talke at lyberty and now is the place ſure for our enbracynges, fortune woulde haue letted oure kyſſynges, but God hathe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured oure loue, and hathe not forſaken ſoo faythfull louers, why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aryeſt thou? here is thy Lucres, whye let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou to embrace her? Eurialus at the laſt forſakig hygh feare, clapſeth her wyth hys armes. I in my lyfe quod he, was I neuer ſo fered, but thou art wel worthy for whome ſuche thynges ſhulde be ſuffered. Theeſe kyſſynges and ſwete enbracynges quod he, no manne ſhulde haue for noughte, nor I (too ſaye trouthe) haue not boughte deare ynoughe ſoo greate a pleaſure. If after my death I myghte lyue, vſynge thy companye, a thouſande tymes wolde I dye to bye thy enbracinges ſo oftene. O howe happye and howe bleſſed, is it a viſion or is it in deede? do I hold the in myne armes? or do I dreame? ſurelye it is thy ſelfe, and the I haue. Lucres was in a lyghte garmente, that wythoute plyghte or wrynkell ſhewed her bodye as it was, a fayre necke, and the lyght of her eyne lyke the bryghte ſonne, gladſome countenaunce and a merye face, her chekes lyke lylyes, medeled wyth roſes, ſweete and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was her laughynge, her breaſte large, and the two pappes ſemynge apples, gathered in Venus gardayne meued the courage of the toucher. Eurialus coulde no longer ſuffer the ſpurre, but forgettynge all fear, and ſobernes layde a parte, ſayde vnto the woman: Let vs nowe taſte of the fruyte of loue, hee preſſed her ſoore, and ſhe too the contrary reſyſted, ſhewynge howe ſhe cared for her honeſtye, and that her loue deſyred no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge but onelye woordes and kyſſes: Vnto whyche Eurialus ſmylynge dyd aunſwere. It is known quod
<pb facs="tcp:13750:20"/>he that I am here, or it is not knowne, yf it be knowne there is no manne that wyll not Iudge the reaſte, yf it bee not knowne, noo more ſhall thys bee, it is thee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of loue, and lette me dye rather than wante that O but is offence quod Lucres. It is offence quod Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialus not to vſe pleaſure whan thou mayſt, ſhoulde I forſake ſuche occaſion graunted and deſired ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye? and takynge her garmente. The ſtryuynge wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that wolde not bee ouercomen, he ouercame Yet dyd hee not quenche thee deſyre of Venus: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prouoked a greater thyrſte, but Eurialus fearyng a further daunger, after he hadde a litle banqueted, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, ſomthyng agaynſte her wyll and mynde, and no man ſuſpected, becauſe he was as one of thee por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toures. As he went through the ſtrete, Eurialus won derynge on hym ſelfe, ſayde. Oh yf the Emperoure ſhuld nowe mete with me, and knowe me. What ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte would this garmente brynge hym in? how wolde he mocke me. I ſhuld be a tale for euery body, and euer a laughter for hym. Neuer wolde hee leue me, tyll tyme that he knewe all, and neades tell him I muſte what thys apparell meaneth, but I woulde ſaye that it were for another woman than this, for perauenture hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth her, and alſo it were not mete too declare hym my loue, for I woulde neuer ſo betray Lucres, that hathe both receyued and ſaued me and thus as he thoughte he ſawe Niſus, Achates, and Plinius, and gothe afore and was not knowne of them tyl he came home, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as chaungynge hys clothes, vnder colour of other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, he telleth the chaunce of the mattere, and as hee remembreth the feare and the Ioye ſo did he in telling feare and rejoice, and in the middes of his feare, ah
<pb facs="tcp:13750:20"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ole that I was quod he, I truſted a woman wyth my hed: ſo was I not councelled of my fathere, whan hee taught me to truſt the fayth of no woman, for that they wexe cruell, deceytfull, chaungeable, and ful of dyuers paſſions, and I yll remembring the leſſon, put my lyfe in a womans handes, what yf anye man had knowne me, when I was charged wyth wheate? what ſhame what ſlaunder hadde bothe I and myne had for euer? The Emperour wolde haue refuſed me, and as lyghte and madde brayned, myght haue eſtemed me, what yf her huſbande had founde me in the cloſet? The cyuyll lawe is cruel to adulterers, but the furoure of the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande would haue had greater payne, the tone hadde ben but ſhort deathe: the other, deathe wyth cruell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes but ſet caſe that he hathe fauoured my lyfe, at the leaſt he wold haue bound me, and ſent me ſhamed vnto the Emperoure. Ye, though I hadde eſcaped his handes becauſe hee hadde no weapon, and I hadde a ſweard by my ſyde, yet hadde he a man wyth hym, and weapons honge at hande vppon the wall, and there was many ſeruauntes in the houſe, the noyſe ſhoulde haue ryſen and the dores ſhyt and I ſhoulde haue ben handled accordynge. Alas madde that I was, no wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but chaunce hath delyuered me from this daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſorowe for chaunce, and it was the readye wytte of her. O truſty woman. O wiſe louer. O noble and excel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent loue, why ſhuld I not truſt vnto the? why ſhoulde I not truſt thy fayth, yf I hadde a thouſande lyues, I durſt truſte the with them all, thou arte faythfull and wyſe, and wyſely thou can loue, and healpe thy louer, who could ſo ſone haue the waye to auoyde them that ſoughte me, as thou had? than haſte ſaued my lyfe, and
<pb facs="tcp:13750:21"/>I vowe it vnto thee, the lyfe that I lyue, is not myne, but thyne, and it ſhall not be greuous vnto mee, for the to leaſe that by the I haue, thou haſte the ryghte of my lyfe, and commaundement on my death. O fayre breſt. O pleaſaunt tongue. O ſwete eyen O freſhe witte, O goodly lymmes and well furnyſhed, whan ſhall I ſee you agayne? whan ſhall I byte that ſame corall lyppe, and here the ſpeke wythin my mouthe? ſhall I neuere handell agayne thoſe rounde breaſtes? O Achates, it is but lytle that thou haſte ſene in any woman in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paryſon to this, the more nearer ſhe is, the more fayrer ſhee is. Lidia, thee fayre wyfe of Candalus, the Kynge was no fayrer: I wonder not yf hee woulde ſhewe her naked vnto Satius for to do him the greater pleaſure for on my faythe, yf I myghts, ſo woulde I ſhewe thee this Lady, for els may I not declare vnto the her beuty nor thou perceyue what ioye I had, but reioyce wyth me, I beſeeche the: that my pleaſure was greater than can be expreſſed with wordes. Thus talked Euria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus with Achates, and Lucres wyth her ſelfe ſayde as muche, but ſo muche leſſe was her gladneſſe that ſhee might truſt none to ſhewe it vnto, and vnto zoſias the durſt not for ſhame tel al.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the mean time a knight called Pacorus, of a noble hous foloing the Emperour, began to loue Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres, and becaus he was fayr and goodli, thought to be beloued and onlye rekened the chaſtitye of the woman to let him. She (as the cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtom of Italy is) beheld euery bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="tcp:13750:21"/>with a lourynge countenaunce, whether it were by diſceyt or craft, leaſt the true loue ſhulde appere. Paco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus rageth and can not be in reaſt tyll he haue felt her minde. The matrones of Scene went oft to viſite the chapel of our Lady of Bethlee in. Hyther was Lucres come wyth two maydens and an olde wyfe. Pacorus folowed her wyth a vyolet wyth golden leaues in hys hande. in the ſtalke whereof, he hadde hydde a letter of loue, wrytten in fyne letters, and haue noo maruayle thereof. For Cicero ſayeth there was ſhewed hym the hole hiſtory of Troy, ſo fynelye written, that it myghte all haue bene cloſed in a nut ſhel. Pacorus offereth the violette too Lucres, recommendynge hym vnto her, and ſhe refuſeth it. He deſyreth her inſtantlye to take it. Take the floure madame quod the olde wyfe, what feare you? there is no pearell, it is but a ſmall thynge: wherein peraduenture ye may do the gentelman plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. She folowed her counſell, and tooke the floure, and whanne ſhe hadde gone a lyttle waye, ſhe tooke it vnto the toone of her maydens, and ſhortelye after they mette wyth two ſcholers, whyche I wot not how lyghtly obtayned the floure of the mayde, and opening the ſtalke, founde the pleaſaunte letter. Nowe after the matronnes of Scene, had founde the louers, that the Emperoure broughte, and after the Courte was come thyther, theſe folke were mocked and deceyued, and lyttle eſtemed, for the clatterynge of harneys de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyted more theſe women then eloquence of learnynge Here vppon grewe greate enuye, and the long gowns ſoughte alwayes howe to lette the courtyers. Than whan the crafte of the vyolet was knowne, ſtrayghte was Menelaus gone vnto, and deſyred to reade the
<pb facs="tcp:13750:22"/>letter he beynge very angry, goeth home, blameth his wyfe, and fylleth all the houſe wyth noyſe. And ſhee to the contrarye denyeth that there is one faute in her and tellynge the hole tale, bryngeth the olde wyfe for wytneſſe. The Emperoure is gone to, complaynte is made, Pacorus is called for, and he confeſſeth the faut aſketh forgeuenes and ſweareth neuer more to vexe Lucres but ryghte well knewe he that Iupyter rather laugheth, then taketh angerly the periuring of louers and ſo the more that he was let, the more hee foloweth the vayne flame.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He winter is come, &amp; the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winds had brought doun ſnows y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> town falleth on plaing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wiues caſt ſnow balles into the ſtretes, and the yong men out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtretes into their windowes. He are had Pacorus gotten occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and had encloſed in waxe an other letter, and putteth it in a ſnowe ball, and caſtyng it vnto Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres wyndowe who wyll not ſaye that fortune ruleth al thyng? one happy hour is more worth to the, than if Mars ſhuld recommende the in his letter too Venus Some ſaye that fortune hathe noo powere in wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menne, I graunte it too ſuche wyſe menne that onlye delyte in vertue: and ſufferynge pouertye ſyckeneſſe, and preſonne canne thyncke them ſelfe bleſſed, whych one yet I neuere ſawe, nor neuer thyncke there was. The commone lyfe of menne neadeth fortunes fauoure. Shee, whome ſhee wyll ſhee auaunceth, and whome ſhe lyſteth, ouerthroweth who hindered Paco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,
<pb facs="tcp:13750:22"/>but fortune, was it not wyſelye handeled, in a violettes ſtalke too hide hys letters and nowe agayne to ſende hys letter cloſed in ſnowe woulde anye man ſaye it myghteeb craftyer, ſo that yf fortune had holpe he had be iudged crafty, and excellently wyſe, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary chaunce brought the ball that fel out of her hand too the fyre, ſoo that the ſnowe ones waſted, and the waxe melted, the letters appeared, which bothe an olde womanne that warmed her, and Menelaus beynge by, dydde reade, and there beganne a newe noyſe, whyche Pacorus dydde not tarye too excuſe, but went hys waye. Thys noyſe healped Eurialus, ſo that it is true that hathe bene ſayd: it is hard defendyng that is dyuerſſy aſſauted. The louers awayted for the ſecond maryage, and there was a lyttle ſtrayte lane betwyxte Lucres houſe and her neyghboures, by the whyche ſettyng hys fete vpon eche wall, he had not ouer harde clymynge to Lucres wyndowe, but thys myghte only he by nyght. Now muſt Menelaus goo into the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and there muſt he lye all nyghte, whyche daye was wayted for of thoſe two louers, as it hadde bene a Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile. The good manne is gone, and Eurialus, chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge hys clothes, is come into the lane, there hadde Menelaus a ſtable, wherein by the teachynge of zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, all the euenynge he lay hydde in the haye, and loo where Dromo came, that was a ſeruaunte of Mene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus, and hadde rule of hys horſes, to fyll the rackes, and harde by Euriolus ſyde dyd pulle out hay, and had taken more, and ſtryken in hym wyth the forcke, hadde not zoſias he alped, who whan he ſawe thee daungere, brother quod he geue me thys worke. I ſhal geue hay to the horſes, thou in the meane tyme, looke that oure
<pb facs="tcp:13750:23"/>ſupper be redy, we muſt be mery whyle oure mayſters is furth, oure mayſtres is better felowe, ſhee is merye and liberall, he is angrye, full of noyſe, couetous, and harde, we are neuer well when he is at home, ſe I pray the what lanke belyes we haue, he is hungry himſelfe to ſterue vs for hunger, hee wyll not ſuffer one moyſte peece of browne breade to be loſte, but the fragmentes of one daye, he keapeth fyue dayes after, and the gob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets of ſalte fyſh and ſalt eles of one ſupper, he kepeth vnto an other, and marketh the cut cheſe, leaſt anye of it ſhulde be ſtolen. The fole that by ſuche wretchednes ſeketh hys ryches, for nothynge is more folyſh than to lyue pore, for too dye ryche, howe muche are we better wyth oure mayſtres? that feedeth vs not onlye wyth veale and kidde, but wyth hennes and byrdes, and ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of wyne. Go Dromo and make the kytchen ſmoke, Mary quod Dromo, that ſhall be my charge, and ſoner ſhall I laye the tables, thanne rub the horſe, I brought my mayſter into the countree to daye that thee Deuyll breke hys necke, and neuer ſpake he woorde vnto me, but badde me whan I brought home my horſes, to tell my mayſtres that he woulde not come home to nyghte but by God quod he, I prayſe the zoſias that at the laſt haſt founde faute at my mayſters condycions. I had forſaken my mayſter, yf my mayſtres had not geuen me my morowe meles as ſhe hathe, lette vs not ſteape to nyghte zoſia, but lette vs eate and dryncke tyll it bee daye, my mayſter ſhall not wynne ſo muche thys mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, as we ſhall waſte at one ſupper. Gladlye dyd Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialus here this, and marked the maners of ſeruants, and thought he was ſerued a lyke, and whan Dromo was gonne, Eurialus aroſe, and ſayd, O happy nyght
<pb facs="tcp:13750:23"/>that throughe thy healpe zoſia, I ſhall haue that haſte broughte me hether, and wyſelye taken heede that I was not diſcouered, and thou ſhalt not ſee that I ſhal be vnkynde. The houre was come, and the glad Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alus, that had paſſed two daungers clame vp that wal, and at the wyndowe wente in where all thynge was ready, and Lucres by the fyre. She whan ſhee ſaw her louer, clapſed hym in her armes, there was embracyng and kyſſyng, and wyth full ſayle they folow their luſts and weryed Venus, nowe wyth Ceres, and now wyth Bachus was refreſhed. Alas, howe longe buſines and howe ſhorte bee the pleaſures ſkante hadde Eurialus one glad houre and lo where zoſias broughte woorde that Menelaus was comme, and marred all the plaie: Eurialus maketh hym readye too departe, ¶ Lucres when ſhe hadde hidden the banket, meteth her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d welcommynge hym home. Welcome quod ſhe my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande, by my trouthe quod ſhe I wened that thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt bene loſte in huſbandrye what haſte thou done in the countrye thus longe? why tarieſt thou not at home thou makeſt mee ſadde wyth thyne abſence, I feare leaſte thou haue ſome other that thou loueſt, theſe huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes be ſo falſe to theyr wyues, yf thou wylte that I ſhall not myſtruſte the, neuer ſlepe oute of my compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, For I can ſlepe no nyghte wythoute the, but lette vs ſuppe here and go to bed, they were than in the hall, where they vſed to dyne, and ſhee ſoughte for too haue kepte hym there tyll Eurialus had ſpace for to goo hys waye, for it requyred ſomme leaſure, but Menelaus hadde ſupped forthe, and haſted towarde hys chamber. Nowe on my faythe and trouthe quod Lucres, thou arte vnkynde, whye dyddeſt thou not rather ſup wyth
<pb facs="tcp:13750:24"/>me, becauſe thou was from hence. I haue eaten noo meate to day, and there were here men of the country that broughte in maruelous good wyne, as they ſayde and yet I taſted not of it, but nowe that thou art come lette vs goo into the celler I beſeche the and taſt yf the wyne be, as they ſay, and ſo hauyng the lanterne in her one hande, pullynge her huſband wyth the other hand wente into the celler, and ſoo longe perced thys veſſell and that, and ſupped wyth her huſbande, tyll ſhee thoughte that Eurialus was gonne, and ſo at the laſte wente wyth her huſbande to the euyll pleaſaunt bed.</p>
            <p>¶ Eurialus in the ſtyll of the nyghte, wente home. And on the morowe, eyther for that it were neceſſarye to take hede or for ſome yl ſuſpecte: Menelaus walled vppe the wyndowe: I thynke as our Cytezens be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectuous and full of coniectures: ſo dyd hee feare thee commodyte of the place, and woulde eſchewe the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon, for though he knewe noughte, yet wyſte hee well that ſhee was muche deſyred, and daylye prouoked by great requeſtes, and iudged a womans thoughte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, whyche hathe as many myndes, as trees hathe leues, and that theyr kinde alway is deſyrous of newe thynges, and ſeldom loue they theyr huſbands whom they haue obteyned. Therefore dyd he folowe the: common opinion of maryed men: to auoyde myſſhap. thoughe it come wyth good lucke. So was theyr me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge lette, and theyr ſendynge of letters alſo ſtopped, for the Tauerner that dwelte behynde Lucres houſe, where as Eurialus was wonte to ſpeke wyth her, and geue her letters: at Menelaus perſwaſion was putte out by the Aldermen, and onely remayned the behoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of theyr eyene, and wyth beckes the louers ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:13750:24"/>eche other, and ſkante myghte they vſe thys vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moeſte poynte of loue, theyr ſorowes were greate, and theyr formentes lyke the death, for they coulde neyther forget, nor vſe theyr loue. Whyle Eurialus doothe ſtudy diligently what auyſe he myght take in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he remembred Lucres councell whyche ſhe wrote vnto hym of Menelaus couſyn Pandalus, and dydde as theſe cunnynge Phiſicians, whoſe manners is, in daungerous ſyckenes to geue indyfferente medecins and in extreme to vſe the laſt medecynes, rather than leue the dyſeaſe incurable, He determined to goo vnto Pandalus, and folowe that waye that afore he hadde forſaken, and when he hadde ſente for hym, called hym into a ſecrete place. Syt downe quod he my frende, I muſt tel the a great thinge that requyreth ſuch thinges as be in the, that is dilygence, fayth, and ſecretneſſe. I would erre nowe haue ſhewed it the, but I knewe the not, nowe I do know the, and becauſe thou arte an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt faythfull man, I loue the and entrete the, ſoo that I knewe nothynge els, it is ynoughe that thy neyghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures prayſe the, and my fellowes too, wyth whome thou haſte entred frendſhyppe, and who and of what ſorte thou arte, they haue toulde me, of whome I haue learned that thou deſyreſt my frendſhyppe, whyche I promyſe nowe vnto the, for thou arte as well worthye myne, as I am thyne. Nowe for becauſe amonge fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des a thynge is done in fewe wordes, what I woulde, I wyll ſhewe the. Thou knoweſt howe the kynde of man is prone vnto loue, whether it bee vertue or vyce, it reygneth euery where, nor no hart there is of fleſhe that ſomtyme hath not felt the pryckes of loue. Thou knoweſt that neyther the wyſe Salomone, nor the
<pb facs="tcp:13750:25"/>ſtronge Sampſon hathe eſcaped from thys paſſyon. Furthermore the nature of a kyndeled hearte and of a folyſhe loue is thys the more it is lette, the more I bourne, wyth nothynge ſoner is thys dyſeaſe healed, than wyth the obtaynynge of the loued. Manye there hath bene, both in our time and in our elder to whome theyr let hathe bene cauſe of cruell deathe, and agayne manye after the thynge obtayned, haue lefte too rage, nothynge is better when loue is crepte into the bones than too geue place too thee rage, for who ſoo ſtryueth agaynſte the tempeſt, ofte tymes ſuffreth wracke and who dryueth wyth the ſtorme eſcapeth. Thys I tell the for that thou ſhalte knowe mee loue, and what for my ſake thou muſte doe, and then what profytte thou ſhalt haue thereby, I wyll ſhewe the all, for nowe I reaken the as one part of my harte. I loue Lucres, and trulye Pandalus it is not by my faut, but by the gouernance of fortune: in whoſe handes is the hole worlde that we inhabyte. The cuſtomes of the countrey were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to me, I thoughte your wemen hadde felte in theyr hartes that they ſhewed with theyr eyene, and that hathe deceyued me, for I thoughte Lucres hadde loued me, becauſe ſhe behelde me pleaſantlye and I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn began to loue her, for I thought ſuch a lady was not vnmeete to bee beloued for loue, and yet dyd I not knowe the, nor none of thy kynne. I loued, and wened to haue bene loued, who is ſo ſtonye harde (beynge lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) that do the not loue (But after I ſawe I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued (leaſte my loue ſhulde be vayne) wyth all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wayes I aſſayed too kyndell her wyth lyke and lyke fyre, for I bourned, and pyteouſlye waſted and ſhame and trouble of my mynde daye and nyghte, dyd
<pb facs="tcp:13750:25"/>maruelouſſye tormente me, and I was ſoo tangled, that with no wayes I coulde eſcape, and at the laſte I contynued ſo long, that the loue of vs both was like ſhe is kyndeled, and I burne, and we bothe pearyſhe, nor we ſe no remedy to our liues, but only thy healpe, her huſbande keepeth her in his chamber. The waker dragon dyd neuer keepe ſo well the golden ſteece: nor Cerberus the entre of hel, as Lucres is kept I knowe your kynrede, and alſo I knowe that ye are noble and ryche, and amonge the beſt of thys towne be loued but who can wythſtande deſtenye? halas Pandalus it was not by my choyce, but by chaunce, and thus ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this matter, it is as yet ſecrete but wythoute it be well guyded, it is lyke, as God forbyd, to brede a greate myſchefe. I peraduenture myghte apeace my ſelfe, yf I went from hence, whiche thoughe it were greuous vnto me, I woulde do for your families, if I thoughte that ſhoulde healpe, but well I knowe her rage, eyther ſhe woulde folowe me, or els yf ſhee were conſtrayned to tarye, woulde kyll her ſelfe, whiche woulde bee vnto your houſe a perpetuall diſhonoure. That I ſente for you, is for your cauſe to wythſtande theſe myſcheues, nor there is none other waye but that thou wylte bee gouernoure of our loue, that the diſſembled fyre maye be ſecreate. I recommende, I geue, and I dowe me holy vnto the, be diligente in this furoure, leaſte whyle it be lette, it flame the more, do ſo muche that we maye mete together, and ſo ſhall the heate bee aſlaked, and made more ſufferable, thou knoweſt the wayes of the houſe, thou knoweſt when the good manne is abſent, thou knoweſt howe too brynge me in, but Menelaus brother muſt be had oute of the waye, whyche wayteth
<pb facs="tcp:13750:26"/>euer diligentlye for theſe inatters, and kepeth Lucres in ſteade of her brother, and marketh dilygentlye her wordes, her lookes, her countenaunce, her ſpyttynges her coughes, her laughes, and eche thynge hre conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth, him muſt I deceyue, and it cannot be wythout the. He alpe therfore I beſeche the, and whan her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande Menelaus is from home, aduertiſe me, and his brothers that taryeth, brynge theym oute of the waye that he neyther take hede to her, nor ſet none other ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, ouer her, whiche yf thou wylte vndertake, and healpe me as my truſt is in the, all is ſafe, for thou maiſt pryuelye, whyle the other be faſte in ſleape, lette me in, and eaſe our fur yous loue, what profyte ſhall enſue of this, I thynke thou vnderſtandeſt by the dyſcrecyon.</p>
            <p>For fyrſt thou ſhalte ſaue the honour of the houſe, and hyde the loue that in no wyſe can bee publyſhed wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute your ſhame. Secondlye thou ſhalt ſaue thy coſen in lawes lyfe, and alſo too Menelaus ſaue a wyfe, too whome it ſhall not be ſo hurteful that ſhee were myne for one nyght (no man knowyng of it) as yf he ſhoulde leſe her, all the worlde wonderynge, whan ſhe ſhoulde folowe me. Dyuers womenne haue folowed theyr lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, what if ſhe determyned to folowe me? what dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour ſhuld it be to your kynne? what mocke among people? what ſhame as well to al the towne as to you? ſome wold peraduenture ſay, put her to deathe rather than ſhe ſhoulde doe thus, but woo bee vnto hym that fyleth him with bludſhedding, and reme dieth one faut by a greater. Myſcheuouſnes be not to be encreaſed but to be leſſed, of two good thynges, wee knowe the beſt is to bee choſen, and of a good and of an ylle, thee good, and of two ylles, the leaſt. Euerye waye is daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous,
<pb facs="tcp:13750:26"/>but thys that I ſhewe the, is leaſte peryllous, by which thou ſhalt not only helpe thyne owne bloude, but alſo me that am almooſt out of my wytte to ſe Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres ſuffre as ſhe dothe for me: who I woulde rather dyd hate me, than I woulde entreate the but thus it is and at thys poynte, and wythoute thy crafte, thy wytte and thy diligence the ſhyp be guyded there, remayneth no hope of health. Helpe therfor both her and me, and ſaue thy houſe from ſhame, and thyncke not that I wyll be vnkynde, thou knoweſt what I may doe wyth the Emperoure, and what thou wylte, I wyll gette the graunted, and thys I promyſe thee on my faythe thou ſhalt be an Earle by patent, and all thy poſteritye ſhall inioye that ſame title, I commit vnto the both Lucres we, our loue and fame, and the honoure of thy kynne, I truſt vnto thy fayth, thou art the arbyte, and al theſe be in thyne handes: Take hede nowe what thou doſte, for lyke as thou mayſt ſaue, ſo mayſt thou ſpyl.</p>
            <p>☞ Pandalus when he heard this, ſmyled and after a lytle pauſe, ſayd (Al this haue I knowne quod he Euri alus, and wolde God it hadde not happened, but nowe as thou ſayeſt: it is at that poynt that I muſt nedes do as thou byddeſt me: excepte I wold ſhame all our kyn and rayſe a great ſlaunder: The woman in dede bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and hathe no power ouer her ſelfe, and wythoute I healpe, ſhe wyl ſle her ſelfe wyth ſome knife, or breke her necke out of ſome wyndow, neyther careth ſhe for her honour, nor for her lyfe, ſhe hathe toulde me her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre, I haue blamed her, I haue buſyed me to quenche the flame, and all in vayne, ſhe careth for noughte but for the, thou art alwayes in her mynd, the ſhe wyſheth,
<pb facs="tcp:13750:27"/>the ſhe deſyreth, and the only ſhe thinketh vpon, often tymes callynge mee by thy name, ſoo is the womanne chaunged by loue, that ſhe ſemeth not the ſame. Halas what pitye and what ſorowe, there was none in all the towne more chaſte or more wyfer then Lucres. It is a maruelous thynge if nature haue geuen loue ſuche lawe ouer the myndes of menne. Thys diſſeaſe muſt be healped, and with none other cure, than thou haſte ſhewed, I wyll goo aboute thys buſynes, and whanne tyme is, I ſhall warne thee, nor I ſeeke noo rewarde of the, it is not the offyce of an honeſt manne too aſke thanke where none is deſerued. I do it to auoyde thee ſame of our houſe, and if thou take any benefyt therby I am not therfore to be rewarded. Yet quod Eurialus for all that I thancke thee, and as I ſayde, I promyſe the to cauſe the to be made Erle, and refuſe not hardly this honoure. I refuſe it not quod Pandalus, but I woulde nat it ſhuld come by thys meanes, if it comme lette it come, I wyl nothynge doe by couenaunte, yf I myghte haue done it by vnknowne too the, that thou myghte haue bene wyth Lucres, I wol de gladly haue done it. Farewell, and thou alſo quod Eurialus, nowe that thou haſt geuen me comforte, make fayne, fynde, or doe by ſome meanes, that we maye be together.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt prayſe me quod Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dalus, and he departed ful glad that he had entred in Eurialus grace. Hoping to be an Earle, where of hee was more deſyrous, in as muche as he ſhewed leaſte, for there be manye men, ſo women lyke, that whan they ſay moſt nay, they would fayneſte, hee hathe gotten by furtheraunce of loue the name of an Earle, and his poſteriars ſhall ſhewe for theyr noblenes a gylted bull.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13750:27"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot longe after ther was afray in the country amonge Menelaus huſbandmen, and diuers of them that had dranke ouer much, were ſlayn, wherfore Menelaus muſt go forth to ſet good order in theſe maters, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lucres ſaid, huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band thou art heauy and weake, and thy horſe goeth hard, borowe therfore ſome ambe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling horſe. And whan he aſked where he might borow any Mary quod Pandalus Eurialus had a very good one, and ſure he wyl gladly lend hym the, if thou wylte I ſhall aſke him. Doe quod Menelaus, and Eurialus aſſone grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted as he was deſired, takyng it for a good token, and to hym ſelfe ſayde, yf thou leape vppon my horſe, I ſhall do the ſame vnto thy wyfe. Nowe the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunt was that at fiue of the clocke Eurialus ſhuld wayte in the ſtrete, and ſhoulde hoope well-yf he harde Pandalus ſing: Menelaus was gone, and the cloudy nyght had couered the heuen, Lucres taryed her tyme in her chambre, and Eurialus was afore the doore, and taryed the token, but hee neyther hearde hym ſynge nor ſpytte, the houre was paſt, Achates meued hym too departe. It was hard to departe, and ymagyned nowe one cauſe nowe another. Pandalus ſang not be cauſe Menelaus brother was lefte there, that ſoughte eche cornes for feare of deceytes, and waked all the whyle. To whome Pandalus ſayde, ſhall we not go to bedde thys nyghte, and I am wonderous ſlepy, I wonder of the that art a younge man, and lyke an olde manne, too whome drynes taketh awaye ſleepe, thou neuer dooſte ſlepe, but before day whan other men do ryſe. Lette vs
<pb facs="tcp:13750:28"/>goo to bedde to what purpoſe doo we watche: Lette vs go quod Agemennon, yf thou wylte, but lette vs looke fyrſt to the dores, yf they be well ſhutte for doubt of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. And whan he was come to the dore, he putte to it, nowe one locke, nowe another, and bolted it. There was a great barre of yron that ſcante two coulde lyfte wherwyth the dore was neuer ſhut, whych whan Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mennon coulde not put to deſyred healpe. Thou ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the dore quod Pandalaus as yf the houſe ſhuld be beſeged, are we not in a ſure city? we are at lyberty in thys towne, and quyetnes is come to vs all. The Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentynes our ennemyes wyth whome we haue warre be farre hence. If thou drede enemyes, thys houſe can not healpe vs. I wyll thys nyghte lyfte noo burdons, my ſhoulders ake, and I am ſore bruſed wythin, I am not mete for the burden, therfore lifte thou thy ſelfe, or let it alone. Wel then quod Agamennon it is ynough, and went to bed. Then quod Eurialus, I wil tary here thys houre to ſe peraduenture yf anye body do appere. Achates that was wyth Eurialus was wery of ſo long taryinge, and preuely curſed Eurialus, whyche hadde kepte hym ſoo longe from ſleape. Yet they caryed not longe after, but they ſawe Lucres throughe a creues, caryinge a lyghte in her hande. Towarde whome Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialus went, and ſayd, god ſpede quod he my dere hart Lucres and ſhe beyng a feard, woulde haue gone her waye, but than remembrynge her ſelfe what man arte thou quod ſhe that calleſt me? I thyne Eurialus am here quod he, ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dore my delite, I haue taried here half this nyght. Lucres at the laſt knew hys voice, but becauſe ſhe feared deceyte, ſhe durſte not open tyll ſhe knewe ſome token that it was hee, and ſo wyth greate
<pb facs="tcp:13750:28"/>labour ſhe remoued the lockes, but becauſe there were many faſteninges to the dore that a womans ſtrength coulde not vndo, ſhe opened it but halfe a foote wyde. Good ynough quod Eurialus, and ſtretchyng him ſelf at laſt gat in and taketh her in his armes. Achates wat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched wythoute. Lucres, eyther for feare or for Ioye ſwowmed in Eurialus armes, and her ſtrengthe fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge wyth pale face ſemed al readye dead, but that her pulce and hete remayned. Eurialus wyth the ſodeyne chaunce affeared, wyſt not what to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o, if I goo hence thought he, the faut of her death ſhal be in me to leue a womanne in ſuch daunger, if I tarye, Agamennon or ſome of the houſe ſhal come, and than I am vndone. Alas vnhappy loue that haſt in the more gal, than hony the bytter wormewod is no more ſoure than thou arte What daungers haſt thou alredy put me in? with how manidethes haſt thou thretened mi hed? and haſt thou lefte me nowe too haue a woman dye in myne armes? why haſt thou not rather ſlayne me? why haſt thou not torne me wyth lyons. Alas how much had it bene that I had dyed in her lappe, than ſhe in my boſome? Loue had ouercome the man, and regardynge not his owne helth, taryed with the womanne, and lyftyng vppe her bodye all be moyſted wyth teres kyſſed her. Alas Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres quod he, where art thou become? where bee thyne eares? why anſwereſt thou not? whye hereſt thou not? open thyne eyes. I beſeche the loke vpon me, ſmile on me as thou art wont, thy Eurialus is hear, he doth em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the, why dooſt thou thus trouble me? I wonder, arte thou gone, or dooſt thou ſlepe? where ſhall I ſeke the? yf thou woldeſt dye, whye dyddeſt thou not warne me that I myghte haue dyed wyth the? yf thou wylte
<pb facs="tcp:13750:29"/>not heare me, my ſworde ſhall ſtrayghte open my ſyde, and wee ſhall boothe dye at ones. Ah my lyfe, my dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, my delyte, my only hope, and my hole health, ſhall I thus leſe the? open thyne eyne, lyft vp thy head, thou art not yet ded, If ele thou art warme, and thy breathe is yet in the, whye doſte thou not ſpeake to me? dooſte thou receyue me of thys ſort? dooſt thou call me to ſuch paſtyme? dooſte thou gy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e me ſuche a nyghte? Ryſe I beſeche the mydewhart, looke on thy Eurialus, I am here and wyth that word the floud of his teres fluſhed ſo vppon her face, that as wyth droppes of water the woman awaked out of her ſlepe, and ſeynge her louer. Alas quod ſhe Eurialus, where haue I ben? why dyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou not ſuffer me to dye? happelye had I dyed in thy armes, and would God I myght ſo dye? eare thou ſhulde departe the towne. Thus talckynge together, they wente into the chamber, where they hadde ſuche a nyghte, as wee iudge the two louers Paris and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena had after he had taken her away, and it was vnto them ſo pleaſanut, that they thoughte Mars and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus hadde neuer none ſuch, thou art quod Lucres my Canimedes, my Ypolitus, my Diomedes. Thou art quod Eurialus my Polexena, my emly, ye, and Venus her ſelfe, and her mouthe and nowe her eyene, and now her chekes he kyſſeth, and ſom tyme caſting doun the clothes, he ſawe ſuche beautye as hee neuer afore ſaw. I haue found more quod he than I wened, ſuche a one ſawe Acteon of Dians, whanne ſhe bathed her in the fountayne what is moore pleaſaunter or more fayrer than theſe lymmes, nowe haue I bought them wyth pearyl, but what thyng ſhuld I not haue ſuffred for the? O fayre necke, and pleaſaunt breſtes, is it you
<pb facs="tcp:13750:29"/>that I touche? is it you that I haue? are ye in my han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des? O round lymmes, O ſwete bodye, haue I thee in my armes? Nowe where dothe pleaſante in the freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my ioye, that no diſpleaſure myghte here after hurte it. Do I holde the or doo I dreme? O pleaſaunte kyſſes, Oh dere enbracynges, O ſweete bytynges, no man lyuinge is more happye than I, or more bleſſed.</p>
            <p>But alas how ſwyfte be theſe houres? Thou ſpytefull nyght, why goeſt thou awaye? abyde Apollo and tarye vnder the earth, why doſt thou ſo ſone put thy horſe in to the chayre? let them repaſt, geue me thys nyghte as thou dyddeſt to Alemena, why doeſt thou Aurora leaue ſoo ſone the bed of Titan, yf thou were as pleaſaunte vnto hym as Lucres is to me, he wolde not ſuffer thee to ariſe ſo earlye. Neuer ſawe I ſo ſhorte a nyghte, yet haue. I bene in Britayne and in Denmarke, thus ſayd Eurialus, and Lucres ſayde no leſſe, nor ſuffered not one kyſſe nor one worde to paſſe vnrecompenced. Hee ſtrayned, and ſhe ſtrayned, and whan they hadde done they were not wearye, but as Athens, roſe frome thee grounde ſtronger, ſoo after battell were they more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrous of warre. The nyghte ended whan aurora toke from the Ocean her dewe here, he departed, and longe after myghte not retourne, by the dayelye watche that was put vnto her, but loue ouercame all thynge, and at laſte they founde waye for theyr metynge, which longe while they vſed.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the mean tyme the Emperour that al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>redy was reconciled to Eugenius, deter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mined to go to Rome. This did Lucres perceiue, for what is that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue knoweth not? or who can deceiue a louer &amp; therfor</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13750:30"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Lucres wrote thus vnto Eurialus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F mi mind could be wroth toward the, I wolde now be angrye with the, for that thou haſte diſſembled thi departing but it loueth the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter then me, and may for no cauſe be meued againſte the. Alaſſe my hert, why haſt thou not told me of the Emperours departure he ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth him redy toward his iourney and I knowe wel y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt not tary behynde, alas what ſhall become of me, what ſhal I do pore woman, wher ſhal I reaſt, yf thou do forſake me, my lyfe laſteth not two dayes. For theſe letters therefore moyſted wyth my teares, and for thy ryghthande, and thy promiſed fayth yf euer I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued any thynge of the, or yf euer thou haſt had anye de lyte by me, haue pyty on thy vnhappy louer. My de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre is not that thou ſhuldeſt tary but that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt take me wyth the, I wyll make as I woulde go in the euenynge to Bethlem, and take but one old woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth me. Let two or thre of thy ſeruauntes be ther, and by force take mee awaye. It is noo greate payne too take one awaye that wolde be gone, nor thynke it noo ſhame, for Parys the ſonne of a Kynge dyd lykewyſe, and thou ſhalte doe noo wronge vnto my huſbande, for hee ſhall algates leaſe mee, for yf it bee not by thy takynge, it ſhall be by deathe, but I am ſure thou wylte not be ſo cruell to leaue mee behynde too dye, that euer hath made more of the than of my ſelfe. Farewell my onelye truſte. To whome Eurialus aunſwered after this facion.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13750:30"/>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Etherto haue I hydde fro the my Lucres my departynge, becauſe thou ſhouldeſt not tourmente thee ouermuche afore the tyme, I knowe thy condicions, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what manner thou ſoroweſte, but the Emperoure departeth not ſo that he ſhal not returne, and whan we ſhall retourne from Rome, thys is in oure waye to oure countrey, and if ſo bee the Emperoure wyll goo anye other waye, if I lyue thou ſhalte ſe me retourne let God neuer ſuffer me to come into my countreye, but make me wander lyke Vlyxes, if I come not hether, confort thy ſelfe therfore my dear heart and be of good cheare, be not ſad, but rather liue merely. Thou ſayeſt thy takynge awaye ſhoulde be the greateſt pleaſure that coulde bee to me, it is trouthe, and greater delyte I coulde not haue, than the alwais at my deſire: But I muſte rather take heede too thy honoure than to my luſte, for the fayth that thou be reſt vnto me, byndeth me to geue the ſuche faythfull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyll as ſhulde be mete for the. Thou knoweſt thou art maryed into a noble familye, and haſte the name of a ryght beautyful and chaſte Lady, and it is not onely in Italye, but aſwell in Teutonia, Panonia, Bohemia, and al the worthye partyes, ſo that if I take the awaye (beſyde my ſhame that for thy ſake I ſet lytle by (what dyſhonoure ſhuldeſt thou doo to all thy frendes? what ſorow ſhuld thy mother take? what ſhulde be then ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the? what rumoure ſhoulde all the worlde heare of the? Lo, Lucres that was called more chaſt then the wyfe of Brutus, and better than Penelope, foloweth an adulterer, not remembrynge neyther her parentes, nor countreye, it is not Lucres, but Ippia, or Medea
<pb facs="tcp:13750:31"/>that folowed Iaſon. Halas what grefe ſhulde it be to me to here ſuch thynges of the? Our loue is yet ſecret, there is no manne that dyſprayſeth the. Thy takynge awaye ſhulde marre all, nor thou were not ſoo prayſed as thou ſhuldeſt then be blamed. But beſydes our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, howe wer it poſſyble that we ſhuld vſe our loue? I ſerue the Emperoure, hee hathe made me ryche and of great power, and I cannot departe from hym with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the loſſe of my ſtate, ſo that if I ſhulde leaue hym, I coulde not conuenientlye entertayne the, if I ſhuld contynuallye folow the court, we haue no reaſt, euerye day we chaunge places. The Emperoure hath taryed noo where ſoo longe as he hathe donne here, and that becauſe of warre, ſo that if I ſhoulde carye the aboute wyth me, and haue the in my Tent as a folower of the felde, what reprefe and ſhame ſhuld it be bothe too the and me? For theeſe cauſes I beſeache the my Lucres put away thys mynde and remember thy honour, and flattter not rather thy rage than thy ſelfe: Another lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer perauenture wolde otherwyſe counſel the, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre the to ronne thy way, that he myghte abuſe the as long as he myght, nothynge regardynge what ſhulde befall of it, whyle he myght ſatifye hys appetite, but he were no true louer that wolde regarde rather his own luſt, than thy fame. I councell the my Lucres for the beſt, tary heare I beſeche the and doubte not in myre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne: what ſoeuer the Emperoure hath to do heare, I wyll ſue to haue it commytted vnto me, that I maye accompanye wyth the wythout daunger. Farewel liue and loue me, and thyncke my fyre noo leſſe than thyns owne, and mooſte contrarye to my mynde I departe. Farewel agayne the delyte and fode of my lyfe.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:13750:31"/>
            <p>¶ Wyth theſe letters the woman ſomwhat had appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed her ſelfe, and aunſwered that ſhee woulde folowe hys councell.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hortelye after, Eurialus wente to Rome wyth the Emperour, wher he had not ben longe, but he was ſycke of an hote ague. The pore vnhappy man whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng in loue, began alſo to burn in ſyck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue had waſted his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth by dolour of the dyſeaſe, lyttle remayneth of hys life, &amp; that ſpirit was rather entertaygned with Phiſicions, than taryed of it ſelf. The Emperour viſyted him day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, confortynge hym as hys ſonne, and commaunded that he ſhulde haue all cure of medecynes that myghte be, but none was of more effecte for hys remedye, then a letter from Lucres, wherby he vnderſtode her helth, whych ſomewhat mynyſheth hys ſycknes, and made hym recouer hys fete, ſo that he was at the coronacion of the Emperoure, and there was made Knyghte. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thys whan the Emperoure went to Peruſia, he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed at Rome, and from thence wente too Scene, all thoughe he were but yet weke and verye grene of hys ſycknes but he myght only behoulde Lucres, and not ſpeke to her. Many letters went betwext them, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne there was practiſinge for her goinge away, thre dayes; dyd Eurialus tary there, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaw no ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of wayes too come to her, that as then was taken from hym, he did aduertyſe hys Lady of his departing but neuer had they ſuch pleſure in theyr conuerſacion as they had diſpleaſure in their departynge. Lucres was in her wyndowe when Eurialus ryd through the ſtrete, and wyth theyr moyſte eyen the one behelde the
<pb facs="tcp:13750:32"/>other, he wept and ſhe wept, and bothe wer diſtrayned with greuous doloures, as they that felte theyr hartes tourne of theyr places. If any man doth not know the dolour of death, let hym conſider the departing of two louers, whiche hath more heuynes and more paynfull tormente. The ſoule ſuffreth in death, for that it parte from the beloued bodye, and the bodye (the ſoule ones departed) ſuffereth not, but whanne two myndes, bee ioyned together ſo muche is the diuiſion more payne full, in ſo muche as the delyte of eyther of them is more ſencyble, and ſurelye heare was not two myndes, but ſurelye as weneth Ariſtophanes one ſoule in two bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes ſo departed not one mynde from another, but one loue and one mynde was in two deuyded, and the harte ſuffred particion. Parte of the mynde wente and part remayned and all the ſences were diſperpled and playned too departe from theyr owne ſelfe. Nor one droppe of bloude remayned in thee louers faces, but only teares and bewaylinges, and very deathe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in theyr vyſages who maye wryte or declare, to thinke the grefes of thoſe myndes, but hee that hathe ones in his life bene like wiſe mad. Laodomia, whan Protheſilaus went to the ſiege of Troi ſnowned, and whan ſhee knewe of hys deathe, dyed. Dido, after the predeſtinate departyng of Eneas, ſlewe her ſelfe. And Percia wolde not lyue after Brutus deathe. But thys oure Lucres, after Eurialus was out of her ſyght, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng to the earthe, was taken vp by her mayde as, and layde in her bedde and when ſhe came too her ſelfe, all purple and golden clothes, and glad apparell ſhe layde a parte, and ware diſpleaſaunt tawny and neuer after was harde ſynge or ſeene laughe, nor by no ſportes, no
<pb facs="tcp:13750:32"/>ioye, nor myrthe, myghte euer be reconforted, in which condicion when ſhe hadde a lytle whyle continued, ſhe fell into ſycknes and becauſe her harte was abſente, the mynde woulde receyue no conſolacion, and at the laſte betwyxte the armes of her much wepyng mother (vſynge vayne confortable woordes) ſhee gaue vp the weryed gooſt, dyſdayninge the ſorowful lyfe.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Vrialus after he had paſſed the ſight of thoſe ein y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhulde neuer again ſe him: neuer ſpake to any bodye in his iourney, but caryed onlye Lucres in hys minde, and thoughte buſilye yf he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne, and at laſt came vnto the Emperoure at Peruſia, &amp; wente with him to Ferrar, to Mantua, to Tridente, to Conſtantia, and to Baſile, and ſo into Hungery, and to Bohemy. But lyke as he folowed the Emperour ſo did Lucres folow hym in his ſlepe &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred him no nightes reſt, whom whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he knew hys true louer to be deed meued bi extreme dolour, clothed hym in mournyng apparell, and vtterly exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all comforte, and yet though the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour gaue hym in mariage a right noble and excellente Ladye, yet he neuer enioied af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, but inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on pitifulli wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſted his pain ful life.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13750:33"/>
            <head>¶ Le. A. to the Reder.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>I this litle boke y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maiſt perceiue mi frend</l>
               <l>The end of loue not fained nor fortunable</l>
               <l>By which right plainly thou maiſt entend</l>
               <l>That loue is no pleſur, but a pai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ꝑdurable</l>
               <l>And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end is deth which is moſt lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table</l>
               <l>Therfore ere thou be chayned with ſuche care</l>
               <l>By others peryls, take hede and beware.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Fyrſt by Eurialus, by whome perceyue thou mayſt</l>
               <l>The beſt it is, to eſchue ſhortlye</l>
               <l>To drynke of the cup, or of it to taſte</l>
               <l>That ſauoured more of gall than of hony</l>
               <l>Alſo I coulde ſhewe the hyſtoryes of many</l>
               <l>That if they by tyme had made reſiſtence</l>
               <l>They myght haue eſchued al ſuch inconuenyence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ There was alſo the noble Troylus</l>
               <l>Whych all hys lyfe, abode in mortall payne</l>
               <l>Delayed by Creſyde whoſe hiſtory is piteous</l>
               <l>Tyll at the laſt Achylles had hym ſlayne</l>
               <l>Yet other there be, whyche in thys carefull chayne</l>
               <l>Of loue haue contynued; all theyr lyfe dayes</l>
               <l>Deathe was theyr end, there was non other wayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ We rede alſo of Piramis and Thiſbe</l>
               <l>Whych ſlew them ſelf by theyr ſeruent loue</l>
               <l>Of Hercules, and of the fayre Ioyle</l>
               <l>Wyth many other, whyche I coulde not attayne</l>
               <l>And of Dido, whiche wyth her ſelfe ſtroue</l>
               <l>For loue of Eneas, whan ſhe coulde not attaine</l>
               <l>Tyll at the laſte ſhe had her ſelf ſlayne</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:13750:33"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13750:34"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13750:34"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
